<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Faith &amp; experience:, or, A short narration of the holy life and death of Mary Simpson, late of Gregories Parish in the city of Norvvich: who dyed, anno 1647 in or about the thirtieth yeare of her age after 3 yeares sicknesse and upwards.  Containing a confession of her faith and relation of her experience, taken from her owne mouth.  To which is added a sermon preached at her funerall, upon Rom. 14. 6,7. / by John Collings.</title>
            <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08802</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5316A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64550737</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 64550737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184283</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08802)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184283)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2857:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Faith &amp; experience:, or, A short narration of the holy life and death of Mary Simpson, late of Gregories Parish in the city of Norvvich: who dyed, anno 1647 in or about the thirtieth yeare of her age after 3 yeares sicknesse and upwards.  Containing a confession of her faith and relation of her experience, taken from her owne mouth.  To which is added a sermon preached at her funerall, upon Rom. 14. 6,7. / by John Collings.</title>
                  <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690.</author>
                  <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690. Life &amp; death of a true Christian deciphered in a sermon.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 51, [3], 81 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Tomlins and are to be sold at his house at the Signe of the Sun and Bible in Pye-Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes Collinges' work "The life &amp; death of a true Christian ..." not found in Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
                  <note>Bound and filmed with Wing A27B and Wing A27aA: The saints duty discoursed from 2 Pet 3, 18 and the saints dignity handled from Eph chap I, v. 7 with directions to both delivered from a chatecheticall dialogue by him that was and is ... London : Printed for William Franckling and are to be sold at his Shop Near the Signe of the George in Norwhich, 1649 -- A plaine and easie catechisme : wherein the grounds and principles of Christian religion are briefly taught and likewise proved by scripture published for the benefit of all / by R.A. London : Printed for William Franckling and are to be sold at his Shop near the Signe of the George in Norwich, 1649.</note>
                  <note>Faith &amp; experience, or, A short narration of the holy life and death of Mary Simpson, late of Gregories Parish in the city of Norvvich : who dyed, anno 1647 in or about the thirtieth yeare of her age after 3 yeares sicknesse and upwards, containing a confession of her faith and relation of her experience taken from her owne mouth, to which is added a sermon preached at her funerall upon Rom. 14. 6,7 -- The life &amp; death of a true Christian : deciphered in a sermon preached upon the 14 Rom. 6,7 vers. at the buriall of Mary Simpson ; a religious young maid, lately living in the city of Norwich.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Simpson, Mary, d. 1647 --  Death and burial.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N. T. --  Romans 14, 6-7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:184283:1"/>
            <opener>
               <date>Decemb. 2. 1648.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have peruſed the precedent Diſcourſe of the Life and Death of a vertuous and godly Chriſtian, entitled <hi>Faith and Experience,</hi> and a Pious and profitable Sermon preached at the ſolemnizing of her Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and approve them both very worthy the Printing and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184283:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> FAITH &amp; EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PERIENCE: OR, A ſhort <hi>Narration</hi> of the holy <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Mary Simpſon,</hi> late of <hi>Gregories</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the City of NORVVICH: Who dyed, <hi>Anno</hi> 1647. In or about the thirtieth yeare of her age, after 3 yeares ſickneſſe and upwards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CONTAINING</hi> A Confeſſion of her <hi>Faith,</hi> and Relation of her <hi>Experience,</hi> taken from her owne mouth.</p>
            <p>To which is added, A <hi>Sermon</hi> preached at her Funerall, upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 6, 7.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Collings,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Phil. 1. 23.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>For I am in a ſtrait betwixt two, having a deſire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Ver. 21.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>For to me, to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Tomlins,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe at the Signe of the Sun and Bible in <hi>Pye-corner</hi> 1649.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184283:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:184283:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Glory</hi> of her <hi>Sex,</hi> AND <hi>Excellency</hi> of her AGE, The truly Noble and Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gentlewoman, M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Philip Hobart,</hi> daughter to Sir <hi>John Hobart,</hi> Knight and Baronet, late of <hi>NORFFOLKE.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Nobleſt Lady,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it were nothing but the daily En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement I ſtand in to that <hi>root</hi> of which you are a <hi>branch,</hi> and to your ſelfe as a Member of
<pb facs="tcp:184283:3"/> this <hi>Family,</hi> It were enough I truſt, to claime a pardon for this Dedication, and I might rather ſeeme to deſerve a check for my ſo long negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, than my preſent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: But the <hi>ſutable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of the ſubject in theſe ſheets, is ſuch, that I dare be confident, you will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not only to <hi>patronize</hi> but alſo <hi>practiſe</hi> it, in what you ſee it yet leading you further to <hi>perfection.</hi> It holds out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you a precious <hi>Example</hi> of one that began ſo ſoone to live <hi>to</hi> God, that ſhe is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy living <hi>with</hi> him. <hi>(Lady)</hi> It is a record of the life and
<pb facs="tcp:184283:3"/> death of one (not unknown in her latter dayes unto you) one far below you in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>birth,</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> while ſhe was here, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more <hi>above</hi> you <hi>now:</hi> And of one, who (I dare ſay) thirſted not ſo much afrer your <hi>greatneſſe</hi> then, as you doe after her <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> now. What vanities are the <hi>excelling</hi> things of this life? They have a ſcantneſſe in their fulneſſe, a glut in their enjoyment, and a ſhort time to live. The greateſt <hi>riches</hi> is in the trueſt <hi>poverty,</hi> and to be <hi>nothing</hi> is to be <hi>moſt.</hi> I am confident <hi>(Nobleſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy)</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:184283:4"/> that you have in ſome meaſure learned, not to call the <hi>Proud, Bleſſed;</hi> nor think that <hi>true happineſſe</hi> conſiſts in <hi>worldly greatneſſe.</hi> It were ſweet if we could learne to eye the creatures as God eyes them, and judge them <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi> that are <hi>moſt gracious.</hi> How the world valued this deceaſed Saint, I know not: Sure I am it was done unto her, as God uſeth <hi>to do to them whom he delighteth to honour.</hi> Why ſhould not we look as God looketh? and not judge the <hi>Peacocke</hi> better meat than the <hi>Partridge</hi> becauſe he hath <hi>gayer feathers.</hi> Read here
<pb facs="tcp:184283:4"/> 
               <hi>(Noble Lady,)</hi> the love Chriſt beares to his <hi>Lambs,</hi> and learne from hence, what it is <hi>to ſeeke the Lord early.</hi> How many of Gods precious ones, attaine not ſo much peace in <hi>threeſcore,</hi> as ſhe had in <hi>thirty</hi> yeares? We uſe to ſay, <hi>more worke is done in two houres in the morning, than in the reſt of the day;</hi> She ſet out early to ſeek him, and ſhe quickly found <hi>him whom her ſoule loved.</hi> She quickly redeemed her loſt time, becauſe ſhe had not loſt much. A <hi>young Saint,</hi> and an <hi>old Devill,</hi> is Satans ſlander of the <hi>way of the Lord,</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:184283:5"/> (the Wiſe man ſaith) <hi>is ſtrength to the upright.</hi> Learne hence alſo <hi>(Nobleſt Lady)</hi> the benefit which you will in time reap from your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun practice of <hi>ſeeking the Lord in ſecret.</hi> How often did this removed Saint meet with God, when ſhe was alone <hi>in the Mount?</hi> God ſpeaks his mind more freely to us, and ſo we may alſo do to him, when he and we are <hi>alone.</hi> Let thoſe whoſe God is their pleaſure, or bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſpend the time in paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dreſsing, which you are better ſpending in <hi>ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the face of him who <hi>will</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:184283:5"/> 
               <hi>be found of them that ſeek him.</hi> You will find your <hi>face</hi> will <hi>ſhine</hi> more than theirs; and what but this hath made it already to doe it? I cannot but thankfully admire the goodneſſe of God, which hath already ſo taken off your <hi>Infant-yeares</hi> from the <hi>Vanities of youth,</hi> and I truſt fully perſwaded you of the truth of that which the world cals Hereſie, <hi>That thoſe are most excellent, who are moſt holy.</hi> The follies of <hi>dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>paints,</hi> and <hi>dances,</hi> are ſo far under <hi>Religion,</hi> that they are below a <hi>ſpirit</hi> that is but truly <hi>Noble:</hi> And I (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce
<pb facs="tcp:184283:6"/> to ſay it) below <hi>yours. (Lady)</hi> we are not ſent hither to <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drinke,</hi> and <hi>riſe up to play;</hi> we needed not a <hi>rationall ſoule</hi> for ſuch <hi>ſenſuall emploiments.</hi> You will (yea I dare ſay you have) found more <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> in an houre ſpent with God, than in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpent in ſuch <hi>company</hi> as doe no good, and ſuch <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes</hi> as <hi>adminiſter no grace to the hearers.</hi> Purſue <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts</hi> and <hi>deſignes,</hi> as Noble as your ſpirit is: remember al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that it is a deſigne too baſe for a <hi>divine ſoule</hi> to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue <hi>Creature-Contentments.</hi> Why ſhould we court the
<pb facs="tcp:184283:6"/> 
               <hi>world</hi> that is made for our <hi>ſervant?</hi> and wait upon a <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> that will Weary us to ſerve it, but never ſatisfie the <hi>expectation</hi> of them that <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue</hi> it? Goe on <hi>(Rarest Jewell)</hi> to make <hi>Religion</hi> your <hi>buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and above all, be much in <hi>ſeeking God:</hi> You have the <hi>key</hi> of Heaven if you have but the <hi>gift and grace of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Let it be your deſigne now as much to excell the <hi>Saints</hi> as it hath been hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to excell the <hi>companions</hi> of your age; purſue it as your worke to get as much <hi>love</hi> from Chriſt, as you have <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> from the witneſſes of
<pb facs="tcp:184283:7"/> your <hi>accompliſhments.</hi> Let not your ambition reſt in indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your ſelfe to creatures; but as you are already the <hi>crowne</hi> of your noble Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and the <hi>honour</hi> of thoſe that labour for your ſoule: ſo ſtill goe on, and reſt not till you be a <hi>jewell</hi> ſet in Chriſts <hi>diademe.</hi> As you have been a Noble Example to this <hi>Family,</hi> in teaching them, it is no diſhonour to learne the <hi>Principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> (by which as I dare ſay your humilitie hath excelled the moſt of your <hi>Equals</hi> (if not in <hi>age</hi> yet in <hi>greatneſſe)</hi> who too uſually can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb facs="tcp:184283:7"/> to be <hi>ignorant</hi> ſo no body knowes it) So you have alſo diſcovered more perfection of <hi>Knowledge</hi> at <hi>thirteen,</hi> than the moſt can boaſt of at <hi>threeſcore.</hi> So now haſte on to <hi>perfection,</hi> and labour to excell as gloriouſly in a ſtrict <hi>walking</hi> with God. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>(Nobleſt Lady)</hi> thoſe that walke neareſt the <hi>Sun</hi> have moſt <hi>light</hi> and <hi>heate:</hi> Perfect the joy of your <hi>Noble</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving <hi>Parent.</hi> And to this end, Let me humbly crave that you would continue to make the word <hi>a light unto your feet,</hi> and <hi>a lanthorne to your paths.</hi> Let your <hi>eyes</hi> be
<pb facs="tcp:184283:8"/> often upon it, and let it be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sit tibi vel oratio aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua, vel le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio, nunc cum deo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere nunc deus tecum, ille te prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis ſuis inſtruat, ille diſponat, quem ille divitem fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerit, nemo pauperem faciet.</hi> Cypr. in Ep. 1. ad Donatum. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</note> your <hi>Eye.</hi> Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>Marcella</hi> (a godly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his age) that he could never come to her, but ſhe was asking him ſomewhat about the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and had ſo high an opinion of her, that he ſayes if himſelfe had any <hi>doubt,</hi> he would aske her <hi>judgement.</hi> O let not much reading there <hi>be a wearineſſe to your fleſh!</hi> They are Gods <hi>Counſels,</hi> and may well be our <hi>Counſellors.</hi> Walke with God <hi>in their light,</hi> write your lines by that <hi>rule.</hi> Read often, and with <hi>judgement,</hi> alwayes carrying your <hi>heart</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:184283:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> with your <hi>eye:</hi> You will find a <hi>glory,</hi> a <hi>majeſty,</hi> a <hi>myſtery,</hi> a <hi>depth</hi> in thoſe lines, which you will never be weary of <hi>fadoming,</hi> though you ſhall never be able to find the <hi>bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</hi> I here preſume to offer to your hands an <hi>Example,</hi> which I am ſure your <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> cannot deſpiſe for the <hi>meanneſſe</hi> of it; She is now more <hi>Noble</hi> than you, and in this <hi>happier,</hi> that ſhe hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie been in Heaven <hi>a yeare</hi> before you. <hi>(Nobleſt Lady,)</hi> your <hi>opportunities</hi> are more; your <hi>talents</hi> of Time, and Parts, are <hi>greater.</hi> Outſtrip all <hi>Examples,</hi> and goe on to be
<pb facs="tcp:184283:9"/> as unparallel'd a <hi>preſident</hi> of <hi>holineſſe</hi> to others, as you are of other <hi>Excellencies.</hi> Now the God of <hi>Grace</hi> fill you with his <hi>fulneſſe,</hi> and be unto you both in life and death <hi>advantage,</hi> and preſerve you, the <hi>crowne</hi> of your ſurviving Noble <hi>Parent,</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of your Sex, the <hi>Comfort</hi> of your Noble <hi>friends,</hi> the <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuer</hi> of the Religious name of your <hi>Family,</hi> and the <hi>joy</hi> of his <hi>Saints:</hi> Which is and ſhall be the continued <hi>prayer</hi> of him, who is ambitious to be accounted,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Nobleſt Lady,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humbly obliged. and devoted ſervant in the Lord Jeſus, JOHN COLLINGS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:184283:9"/>
            <head>TO THE Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe ſheets are partly <hi>my owne,</hi> and partly <hi>anothers:</hi> For that part of them that is not my <hi>owne,</hi> it is a Relation of the precious <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> of one that was lately <hi>Ours,</hi> but both <hi>then,</hi> and much more <hi>now Chriſts.</hi> The <hi>Relation</hi> was brought to my hands many <hi>Moneths</hi> ſince, but my crowd of occaſions hindred me from
<pb facs="tcp:184283:10"/> peruſing of it. I ſhall now give thee a true account of it: The <hi>Relation</hi> was penn'd from her mouth by a faithfull friend, nor have I injured her or thee in the tranſcribing of it, having only rank'd the <hi>Articles of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion</hi> in ſuch order as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived moſt ſutable, and made a ſupply ſometimes both there and in the Relation, of a word or two, where was ſome defect through the <hi>neglect,</hi> or <hi>miſtake</hi> (poſsibly) of the first Pen-man; and in ſome places where her phraſe (though ſafe if ſafely underſtood) was more <hi>dark</hi> &amp; ſubject to <hi>ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie,</hi> I have given thee her ſenſe in a clearer and leſſe ambiguous
<pb facs="tcp:184283:10"/> terme. I will aſſure thee, I have neither added nor ſubſtracted any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing (which I conceive) materiall. For what is <hi>mine</hi> in theſe ſheets, It is a ſhort Copy of a <hi>Sermon</hi> at her <hi>Buriall,</hi> it was <hi>compoſed</hi> in a ſhort time, and <hi>tranſcribed</hi> with as much haste. I had rather <hi>profit</hi> thee by <hi>plainneſſe</hi> than <hi>tickle</hi> thee with <hi>exactneſſe:</hi> I am ſure the Sermon hath rather loſt than got by keeping in my Study. I was willing for thy good to let it wait upon her <hi>memorie,</hi> who while ſhe lived, we were all ſo much beholden to. The <hi>plainneſs</hi> and <hi>meanneſſe</hi> of the Sermon will tell thee (I hope) I ſend
<pb facs="tcp:184283:11"/> it not to thee to beg <hi>Honour,</hi> but to <hi>ſerve</hi> thy ſoule in the <hi>meaneſt</hi> place. Reader, thou haſt here a Sermon proved by a freſh <hi>Experience.</hi> O adde ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Proofe,</hi> requite my paines by letting the truth delivered have a witneſse in thy <hi>boſome.</hi> Beleeve it Reader, thou haſt before thy eyes, in theſe ſheets, a <hi>Rule,</hi> and a <hi>Preſident.</hi> It is Gods word to thy ſoule, <hi>Goe thou and doe likewiſe.</hi> If thou readeſt the <hi>Relation,</hi> thou wilt ſee what is got by <hi>ſeeking God early,</hi> to what a <hi>pitch</hi> of grace a Saint may reach; the right <hi>frame</hi> of a <hi>ſober</hi> Goſpell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirit, the picture of a Saint.
<pb facs="tcp:184283:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> If thou readeſt and gaineſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, thank thy owne baſe heart. Here's a deſcription of a true Chriſtian, a ſight of him, in a Copy, and a Picture. Certainly ſomething may be got for thy and my ſouls profit from either. If thou gaineſt any thing, bleſſe thy God, and pray for him, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Norwich, <date>Nov. 20. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Ieſus, JOHN COLLINGS.</signed>
               <pb facs="tcp:184283:12"/>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184283:12"/>
                  <head>Faith and Experience.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>A ſhort <hi>Explanation</hi> of her ſelfe, concerning divers <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Faith;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuch as are moſt <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally</hi> neceſſarie to ſalvation: Taken from her owne mouth.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <div type="articles_of_faith">
                     <div n="1" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning the God-head.</head>
                        <p n="1">I. <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
                           <hi>Believe</hi> there is a <hi>God,</hi> and that this God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> infinite. 1. In <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> 2. In <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> and in <hi>Being,</hi> that there are 3 <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> in the divine <hi>Being,</hi> The <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> the <hi>Sonne,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                           <pb n="2" facs="tcp:184283:13"/> each one God, and yet in being but <hi>one God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning the way to come to know God.</head>
                        <p n="2">II. <hi>I believe,</hi> that this God is made <hi>knowne to us,</hi> by his <hi>Word</hi> and by his <hi>Workes:</hi> That there is a way of the <hi>knowledge of God,</hi> by the <hi>Scripture;</hi> and that there is a way of the <hi>knowledge of God</hi> in a more <hi>ſpeciall</hi> way, wherein God [by his <hi>Spirit]</hi> revealeth himſelfe to his people <hi>experimentally;</hi> yet accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Scripture.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning the Word of God; the holy Scriptures.</head>
                        <p n="3">III. <hi>I believe,</hi> That the holy <hi>Scripture</hi> is the <hi>very Word</hi> of God. 1. Becauſe it declares the <hi>Wiſedome</hi> of God. 2. Becauſe it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184283:13"/> diſcovers our <hi>vileneſſe</hi> and <hi>folly.</hi> 3. Becauſe it puts us upon <hi>purity.</hi> 4. Becauſe it reveales to us the great <hi>myſteries</hi> of <hi>Salvation. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> That God by this his Word is made knowne to us. 1. As he is in himſelfe by his <hi>Nature.</hi> 2 By his <hi>Names,</hi> which are his <hi>Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes;</hi> or, [2. his Names of <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.]</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning Gods works of Creation; and Providence.</head>
                        <p n="4">IV. <hi>I believe,</hi> That this God is further made knowne to us, by his <hi>Workes</hi> of <hi>Creation. I believe</hi> His work of <hi>Creation,</hi> was his <hi>Creating</hi> of all things in heaven and earth. <hi>I believe,</hi> That God did <hi>create</hi> all things in heaven and earth: I put a difference between <hi>Creating,</hi> and <hi>Making:</hi> To make is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſomething out of ſomething:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184283:14"/> To <hi>create</hi> is to produce <hi>ſomething</hi> out of <hi>nothing. I believe,</hi> that God did <hi>make</hi> all things in heaven and earth, for man, and man onely for himſelfe and his ſervice.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning the Creation of man in ſpeciall, and the ſtate of innocency in which he was created.</head>
                        <p n="5">V. <hi>I believe,</hi> That God made man only for himſelfe and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. <hi>I believe,</hi> That man was made in ſuch an eſtate, whereby he was able to ſerve <hi>God,</hi> by that divine grace which was put into him by God himſelfe. <hi>I believe,</hi> That man (being thus created) was infinitely ingaged to ſerve his God, becauſe hee had thus made him, and all things elſe, for his uſe and ſervice. <hi>I believe,</hi> That all that God made [amongſt which was man] was <hi>exceeding good,</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184283:14"/> whatſoever was afterward not <hi>good</hi> was through the <hi>defect</hi> of the <hi>Creature. I believe,</hi> That man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus <hi>made</hi> and engaged to <hi>ſerve</hi> his God, yet was made <hi>liable</hi> to fall.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning the Fall of man.</head>
                        <p n="6">VI. <hi>I believe,</hi> That Man <hi>fell,</hi> and that <hi>wholly</hi> from God, and that being thus fallen, God might juſtly have taken advantage upon fallen man, and have caſt him and his poſterity off, to all <hi>Eternity,</hi> as hee did the fallen Angels.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="article">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Concerning Gods workes of grace.</hi> 1. <hi>Of Election.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p n="7">VII. <hi>I believe,</hi> There is an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Grace;</hi> and that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that <hi>Election</hi> there ſhall be but a <hi>few</hi> that ſhall participate
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184283:15"/> of the way of <hi>recovery</hi> by <hi>Ieſus Christ.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning the work of Redemption and Reconciliation.</head>
                        <p n="8">VIII. <hi>I believe,</hi> That there was no <hi>cauſe</hi> in man being fallen, to move God to <hi>recover</hi> him from that fallen eſtate: but onely he was moved from <hi>his owne bowells. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> [being moved ſo from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe] hee found out a way him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for mans <hi>Recovery. I believe,</hi> That the <hi>way</hi> ſo found out, and the meanes by which alone fallen man can be reſtored, was by a <hi>Mediator</hi> taking upon him our <hi>Nature,</hi> that ſo he might pacifie the <hi>wrath</hi> of God for the ſinne of our <hi>Nature,</hi> that wee might thereby be fit to live with God in our <hi>Nature.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning Originall ſinne.</head>
                        <p n="9">IX. <hi>I believe,</hi> [That our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184283:15"/> was ſinfull] and that the ſin of our <hi>Nature</hi> was the cauſe of all our <hi>ſorrowes temporall,</hi> and <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall;</hi> we dyed <hi>ſpiritually</hi> at the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> of the fall, and all ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly dye a <hi>temporall</hi> death, and only ſome ſhall be delivered from dying <hi>eternally.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="article">
                        <head>Further. <hi>Concerning the worke of Redemption and Reconciliation, the ſole Redeemer, the fruit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, the myſterie of convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p n="10">X. <hi>I believe,</hi> That as the whole <hi>Trinity</hi> did worke in the <hi>Creation</hi> of the world, ſo they did alſo <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually</hi> worke in the worke of our <hi>Redemption:</hi> God the Father and the Holy Ghoſt <hi>ſending,</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> being <hi>ſent</hi> and <hi>comming.</hi> [But] <hi>I believe,</hi> that Chriſt hath [alone] <hi>performed</hi> the worke of <hi>redemption</hi>
                           <pb n="8" facs="tcp:184283:16"/> and <hi>reconciliation,</hi> fully ſatisfying the <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of God to the utmoſt for <hi>all his. I believe</hi> alſo, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man in the world is <hi>beholding</hi> to God for <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of their <hi>lives,</hi> and of the <hi>creatures,</hi> and that for the preſent they are reprieved from hell and damnation. <hi>I believe,</hi> That <hi>Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation</hi> is to be found in no other, but in <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> who is the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone great <hi>Reconciler</hi> betwixt God and his people. <hi>I believe,</hi> That the worke of <hi>Redemption</hi> is a great <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie:</hi> for the divine <hi>Nature</hi> to take upon him the <hi>humane nature,</hi> O it is a great <hi>Myſterie.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I believe</hi> alſo, That it is a great <hi>Myſterie,</hi> in regard of the <hi>way</hi> of its particular <hi>conveyance.</hi> And that Chriſt hath not onely <hi>purchaſed</hi> this ſalvation, but alſo makes a particular <hi>Declaration</hi> of it. 1. By his <hi>Word.</hi> 2. By the <hi>Worke</hi> of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184283:16"/> 
                           <hi>ſpirit on the ſoule.</hi> And 3. By the <hi>witneſſe of the ſpirit. I believe,</hi> That in this worke, Jeſus Chriſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed <hi>ſtrength</hi> for every beleever, to withſtand <hi>Sin, Death,</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning Perſeverance in Grace.</head>
                        <p n="1">XI. <hi>I believe,</hi> That by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt there is <hi>power</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for every <hi>Believer,</hi> to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>Sinne, Death,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> [Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that] the fallen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the Devils, as they were the firſt occaſion of the fall, ſo they are great hinderers of this worke of [Grace and] <hi>Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they having us at ſuch an <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="article">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Concerning Death and the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> and <hi>the Immortality of the ſoule.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p n="12">XII. <hi>I believe,</hi> That all men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184283:17"/> to Gods appointment muſt [dye, and] <hi>continue</hi> in the Grave. The <hi>bodies</hi> [I meane] of every <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Woman,</hi> that ſo they might be made fit for <hi>eternity,</hi> ſome for eternall wrath, others for eternall glory. <hi>I believe,</hi> That the ſoules of all immediately after death, goe <hi>to God</hi> that gave them, there to give an account for what they have done in the fleſh. <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> that the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the Saints to <hi>grace</hi> here, and <hi>glory</hi> hereafter, is purchaſed by the <hi>Death, Reſurrection,</hi> and <hi>Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>I believe,</hi> That the <hi>ſame bodies</hi> both for <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and <hi>forme,</hi> every <hi>joint</hi> and <hi>limbe</hi> ſhall <hi>riſe</hi> againe, and not a <hi>bone</hi> ſhall be wanting. A <hi>ſubſtantiall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> both for <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>bones,</hi> that I prove by Chriſts <hi>reſurrection</hi> who was raiſed with the ſame body.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Object. But, you will ſay, Chriſts
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184283:17"/> body lay but three dayes in the Grave, and ſo his body was not rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the duſt, but ours will lye ſo long that our bodies ſhall be turned into duſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Anſ. I Anſwer.</hi> The ſame <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> that made the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> out of the <hi>duſt,</hi> the ſame power can raiſe our <hi>bodies</hi> again, although turned to <hi>duſt:</hi> So that the worke of <hi>Reſurrection</hi> is a <hi>curious</hi> worke, and ſecretly wrought in the <hi>wombe</hi> of the earth, as the child is ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought in the <hi>womb</hi> of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. There ſhall be the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to make the bodies of in the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> at the <hi>laſt day</hi> that there was when God firſt formed the body of <hi>Adam,</hi> viz. The <hi>Duſt</hi> of the earth. The ſame power ſhall raiſe all our <hi>bodies,</hi> though turned to duſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="article">
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:184283:18"/>
                        <head>Concerning the day of Iudgement.</head>
                        <p n="12">XII. <hi>I believe,</hi> That Chriſt ſhall come <hi>perſonally</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> the world, and that with an <hi>audible</hi> voice, &amp; by the <hi>word</hi> of his mouth, he ſhall <hi>raiſe</hi> the <hi>dead;</hi> And that at the day of <hi>judgement</hi> all the ſins of the godly ſhall be laid upon <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ.</hi> They here in the world <hi>accuſe</hi> themſelves for ſinne, and ſo ſhall be <hi>excuſed</hi> at the <hi>laſt</hi> day. It is the office of <hi>conſcience</hi> to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe</hi> here or hereafter. <hi>Conſcience</hi> having done its <hi>office,</hi> there ſhall be nothing objected againſt them at that day, But they ſhall heare that bleſſed <hi>Sentence, Come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my Father.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="article">
                        <head>Concerning Glorification &amp; heaven.</head>
                        <p n="14">XIV. <hi>I believe,</hi> The godly at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184283:18"/> the day of <hi>Iudgement</hi> ſhall heare that bleſſed Sentence, <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdome prepared for you before the beginning of the world.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I believe,</hi> In <hi>Heaven</hi> there ſhall be no <hi>Infant of dayes,</hi> nor <hi>old man of yeares.</hi> The <hi>corruptible</hi> life of of the <hi>creature</hi> ſhall not inherit <hi>eternall life;</hi> there ſhall no <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> no <hi>deformity</hi> what ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company that <hi>life;</hi> there ſhall be no <hi>eating</hi> nor <hi>drinking</hi> in it, but <hi>ſinging Hallelujahs</hi> to God for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. I will conclude with the Pſalmiſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>Pſalm. 139.</bibl> 
                           <hi>I will praiſe the Lord for I am fearefully, and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully made: marvellous are thy works, and that my ſoule knowes right well.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                  </div>
                  <div type="interjection">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:184283:19"/>
                     <p> Reader! Thou haſt thus far read her <hi>Faith;</hi> now hear her <hi>Storie,</hi> that was faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully taken from her own mouth: And ſo alſo was this that followes, being the Relation of Gods dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Pſalm. 34. 8.</bibl> 
                        <hi>Taſte and ſee how good the Lord is.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Pſalm. 66. 16.</bibl> 
                        <hi>Come and I will tell you what God hath done for my ſoule.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>I ſhall ſpeake nothing but what God hath done <hi>in</hi> me, and <hi>for</hi> me.</p>
                     <p>THe firſt worke that God ever wrought in my ſoule was a worke of <hi>conviction.</hi> He convinced
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184283:19"/> my ſoul of the ſin of <hi>Sabboth-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</hi> I found much oppoſition to that worke, and it was ſome ſpace of time before I could get ſtrength againſt that ſinne: but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and anon I was given up to the ſinne againe, which was (yet) a <hi>burthen</hi> to my ſoule. I had no <note place="margin">Obſerve Gods firſt worke in converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                        <hi>ſtrength</hi> againſt it for the preſent, till at length the Lord was pleaſed to diſcover another ſtrength than that I had from my ſelfe, which was the <hi>ſtrength of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> to overcome this <hi>corruption. A ſight</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                        <hi>of ſinne without a ſight of Chriſt</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                        <hi>is not ſaving of it ſelf.</hi> But a ſight of ſin wrought by God, God lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not the worke till hee hath ſhewne the ſoule the ſight of Chriſt. That I conceive is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving work.</p>
                     <p>One time me thought my fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the night preſented to me ſinne in a <hi>lump,</hi> with a ſight of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184283:20"/> that Chriſt which afterwards I ſaw more <hi>perfectly.</hi> It was thus: me <note place="margin">Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> thought I ſaw ſin ſet out in a <hi>market</hi> upon a <hi>ſtall.</hi> The commodity was vended to none but it brought <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>confuſion</hi> of face to thoſe that ſet it forth to Sale; and me thought I ſaw likewiſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> comming, &amp; owning the owner of the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, which in time I ſaw he fully did in me; and it was a <hi>refreſhing</hi> for the preſent to my ſpirit that I ſaw he would do it for me, though he came not preſently.</p>
                     <p>The next thing I apprehended according to the truth of the word was, <hi>that A Christ was come,</hi> to doe ſuch things as are declared in the word. This I no ſooner apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <note place="margin">Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> but I was ſet upon with <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations;</hi> To queſtion <hi>whether there was a Chriſt or no, &amp;c.</hi> Satan wrought <hi>Secretly</hi> and <hi>Subtilly.</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant of his <hi>myſteries,</hi> was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184283:20"/> for a certaine time given up to <note place="margin">Sathans ſubtilty.</note> the <hi>temptation.</hi> But as Satan wrought <hi>ſecretly</hi> and <hi>ſubtilly,</hi> ſo God wrought <hi>inviſibly</hi> and <hi>migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily,</hi> to the ſuppreſſing of him. For aſſoon as God delivered me out of the <hi>temptation,</hi> I diſcovered a Chriſt, fully according as he is <hi>revealed</hi> in the word to be the Chriſt, the ſon of God, my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; then I could ſee my great deliverance out of the <hi>temptation,</hi> and not till then, then I ſaw that if God had deliverd me finally up to the <hi>temptation,</hi> I had denyed God, and his Chriſt, and his word, and whatſoever he is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be known by.</p>
                     <p>The next thing after I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended a <hi>Chriſt come,</hi> was how he ſhould be made knowne to his people to be their <hi>Ieſus,</hi> which in time by the miniſtry of the word God was pleaſed to make
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:184283:21"/> known unto me, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>God gave Chriſt, to dwell in the hearts of his people, by grace,</hi> and then my ſoule began to be panged with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of that <hi>grace of Regeneration.</hi> I no ſooner had a deſire of grace, but I fell to queſtion the <hi>truth of</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Satans ſubtilty.</note> 
                        <hi>Grace,</hi> where the Devill was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till as in any <hi>temptation,</hi> but the Lord by his mighty power over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him for me, where the <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of God appeared to me in <note place="margin">Gods goodneſſe. Note, wher it was ſhe met with God.</note> the time as well as in the ſtrait. I attended much upon <hi>hearing the word,</hi> by which God anſwered all my doubts, and repelled Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temptations: Then Satan tempted me to doubt <hi>of the truth of Gods word.</hi> I ſaid <hi>Bleſſed be God! if</hi> that word be <hi>truth;</hi> and no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was I from under the noiſe of the preacher, but I was as full of doubting as before. God took me out of that condition, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184283:21"/> me into another <hi>trouble,</hi> which was Satans ſubtilty (by Gods permiſſion) for my good. The Devill implyed Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to taint my ſoule with monſtrous, and groſſe <hi>errours.</hi> But God of his infinite mercy would not ſuffer me to ſpeak againſt the truth (with thoſe Inſtruments of Satan) though I could not plead for it. The Errours inſinuated were theſe. 1 <hi>That there is free will</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Obſerve her ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome of our new Truths.</note> 
                        <hi>in man to doe good.</hi> 2 <hi>That there is no Electtion.</hi> 3 <hi>That none are irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilably loſt.</hi> 4 <hi>That Chriſt was not come in the fleſh.</hi> 5 <hi>That moſt of the Scriptures were to be underſtood in an allegory.</hi> Theſe opinions they were very diligent to draw my ſoule to; I being weake in my ſelfe had fallen from the truth had it not beene for the power of God and his rich condeſcention to me. I told the parties if I did not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184283:22"/> give them arguments in one week, that then I would not ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, but for, that which they held; and then the Lord ſet me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly to ſtudy the divine Scriptures, which through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or miſunderſtanding, I thought ſome thing in the word was <hi>for them,</hi> and ſomething <hi>againſt them,</hi> while I thought to attaine it only by <hi>reading;</hi> but when I ſaw it was too hard, then the Lord was pleaſed to help mee by <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Obſerve the right way to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> and <hi>prayer,</hi> and ſtrong cryes, and then, and not till then, did I know what it was to pray <hi>out of an apprehenſion of wants.</hi> I <note place="margin">A right frame of ſpirit in ſeeking di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> tooke the truth, and errour, with an equall hand, neither cleaving in my affections to the one, nor to the other, till God was pleaſed to reveale it to me; but I deſired God to ſhew me which was the <hi>truth,</hi> and he did accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184283:22"/> Thoſe Scriptures I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended made againſt the truth, he ſhewed me they made for the truth. Now when the Lord had revealed himſelfe in this to me, I was earneſt with God that I might not only <hi>know</hi> theſe truths, but I might be able to <hi>hold</hi> out theſe truths ſo as to ſtop the mouths of <hi>gainſayers:</hi> 2 dayes after Gods <hi>revealing</hi> himſelfe, theſe parties came, and God gave me to ſpeak that they were not able to anſwer, and at that time God gave me a <hi>promiſe</hi> Joh. 1. 50. <hi>Ieſus anſwered</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Joh. 1. 50.</note> 
                        <hi>and ſaid unto him, becauſe I ſaid unto thee I ſaw thee under the figtree, beleeveſt thou? thou ſhalt ſee grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">A particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar promiſe applyed generally.</note> 
                        <hi>things then theſe;</hi> with which my Soule ſtood a little <hi>amazed</hi> what ſhould be the <hi>greater</hi> things that ſhould be revealed? I found then, that they ſhould be theſe truths made known by <hi>experience</hi>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:184283:23"/> 
                        <hi>to my Soule.</hi> I went away rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>hope</hi> to obtaine it; from this work of God I concluded that there was a <hi>work of grace</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, which he would carry on to <hi>perfection.</hi> The next thing I thought upon, was to ſet downe to account the loſſe it would coſt me to hold out theſe truths to the utmoſt, which was the loſſe of the favour of friends, <hi>diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagment</hi> to creatures, but there was an <hi>ingagement</hi> to God, which made me reſolute to ſtick to the truth, whatſoever it coſt, in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of God: and then I ſaw a neceſſity of <hi>walking more cloſe</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe in Piety.</note> 
                        <hi>with God,</hi> in the wayes of his <hi>worſhip,</hi> ſeeking to him for <hi>ſtrength,</hi> in every eſtate and <hi>condition</hi> what ever he put me into; whether <hi>ſpirituall</hi> or <hi>temporall.</hi> When Satan ſaw that I indeavored to be <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>ſtrict,</hi> he ſet before me a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184283:23"/> of <hi>perfection,</hi> by his ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of me <hi>perfection;</hi> I by the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of Gods grace had ſuch a ſight of <hi>imperfection,</hi> that I was <note place="margin">Satans policy.</note> loſt in my owne <hi>apprehenſion,</hi> and concluded, that there was no grace becauſe there was ſo much <hi>imperfection,</hi> and then God was pleaſed for to make me appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that Jeſus Chriſt muſt come, and take away the <hi>imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> of our duties, the <hi>defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of ſinne as well as the <hi>guilt,</hi> which he did by revealing thoſe <hi>promiſes</hi> which he cauſed me to reſt upon in that 2 Cor. 5. 21. <hi>for</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 21.</note> 
                        <hi>he had made him to be ſinne for us who knew no ſinne, that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him.</hi> Mat. 1. 21. <hi>He ſhall ſave his</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 1. 21.</note> 
                        <hi>people from their ſins,</hi> which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved ſhould be done for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though they were not done for the preſent; ſo that I ſaw
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184283:24"/> Chriſt to be of uſe, to clenſe me, <note place="margin">Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeene before <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</hi>
                        </note> before I ſaw him <hi>Iuſtifying</hi> my perſon, which was a great refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my Spirit; then I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to make uſe of thoſe <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons</hi> that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, which are not <hi>carnall</hi> but <hi>mighty through God for the pulling downe ſtrong holds, &amp;c.</hi> and the Lord did give me much <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> by <hi>communion</hi> with himſelfe, ſo that I could goe to him more <note place="margin">The ſpirit of Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> freely then to any <hi>creature</hi> under heaven, and the more <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> I had with him the more <hi>ſtrength</hi> I had againſt <hi>temptation</hi> and <hi>corruption:</hi> I found it to be <note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent prayer.</note> the moſt excellent means under heaven, the more frequent the more familiar with God; and now I began in ſome meaſure to <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended</hi> what a <hi>temptation</hi> was, in a time of <hi>temptation,</hi> which was halfe a deliverance out of it: this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:184283:24"/> through the mercy of God in Chriſt Jeſus I found by <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> in <hi>prayer,</hi> and about <hi>prayer.</hi> I found firſt the ſubtilty of Satans <hi>temptations,</hi> wherein I found him <note place="margin">Sathans malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the worke of prayer.</note> to be as great hinderer of that work of <hi>prayer</hi> as of any other; if he cannot keep from it, he will <hi>afflict</hi> and <hi>diſcourage</hi> in it; and notwithſtanding all this, I was by Satan put upon it to queſtion my <hi>Condition</hi> againe, but God gave me a word at the ſame time to ſtay my Soule upon, it was Gods token to know <hi>Paul</hi> by, <hi>behold he prayes,</hi> from which words I ſaw God took ſpecial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of thoſe that <hi>praid</hi> and waited upon him; and when the Devill ſaw me bent upon <hi>prayer,</hi> then he put me upon <hi>prayer,</hi> which in time I ſaw was his work, and in time it proved greatly to the Devils <hi>diſadvantage,</hi> and much for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184283:25"/> my <hi>incouragement.</hi> I found by <hi>experience</hi> that he is like an Ape <hi>imitating</hi> what ever good God does in the Soule: and there is need of much of God to diſcern his policy in this particular; he hath <hi>counterfeit grace</hi> as well as God hath true <hi>grace;</hi> and he hath evill <hi>Ioy,</hi> as God hath <hi>Soule-refreſhing, reviving</hi> and ſweet <hi>conſolation,</hi> he will have <hi>ſcriptures</hi> as well as <hi>God,</hi> only his are to <hi>diſcourage</hi> from <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and Gods to <hi>incourage;</hi> all the <hi>wayes</hi> of Satan are evill, and all the <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                        <hi>wayes</hi> of God are <hi>exceeding good,</hi> and his <hi>paths</hi> are very <hi>pleaſant.</hi> When Satan ſaw he could not defile my ſoule by <hi>one temptation,</hi> he ſets up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me by <hi>another,</hi> and with mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>temptations</hi> all at once. So that he put my Soule into a darke miſt by his <hi>temptations,</hi> and I walked ſadly for ſome Dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to the wonderment of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184283:25"/> my <hi>friends</hi> that were about me. I could not expreſſe my ſelfe in any thing becauſe my <hi>temptations</hi> and tumults in my ſpirit were ſo high in many things, but the <hi>Lord</hi> at that time did much <hi>stay</hi> and refreſh my <hi>ſpirit</hi> with the word Iſay. 50. 10. whereby <note place="margin">Iſa. 50. 10.</note> I ſaw that my condition at that time was no other, then was incident to Gods owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo the Lord carried me on from one condition to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſtraights, and revealed no more to me for the preſent then this, that my <hi>condition</hi> was ſuch as was incident to the <hi>Saints.</hi> The next thing I ſaw was <hi>that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">More Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</note> 
                        <hi>Chriſt was the Iuſtifier of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and that <hi>Iuſtification was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed</hi> to the ſoule in a way of <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving:</hi> and then my Soule ſaid, oh! that I could <hi>beleeve</hi> on him that <hi>Iuſtifies the ungodly.</hi> The
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184283:26"/> more underſtanding I had of God in that way, the more I ſaw of mine owne <hi>filthineſſe:</hi> I ſaw filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the holy things of God, as performed by me, ſo that I found that word of the Apoſtle good <hi>That in me (that is in my fleſh) dwells no good thing, but to will is (by the</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> 
                        <hi>grace of God) preſent with me, but how to doe good I found not;</hi> which (through the grace of God) wrought in my Soule a reſtleſſe deſire after a <hi>Chriſt</hi> in a way of <hi>beleeving,</hi> that ſo I might fetch <hi>ſtrength</hi> from Chriſt, for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing of every <hi>corruption,</hi> that I might know whether I were in a ſtate of <hi>Iuſtification;</hi> this I found, that the more Satan temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, that his temptations were as a weapon put into my hand to fight againſt himſelfe withall; through the mighty <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration</hi> of God, <hi>his ſtrength was</hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:184283:26"/> 
                        <hi>made knowne in my weakneſſe.</hi> Still <note place="margin">Faith hard.</note> God put into my Soule ſuch a reſtleſſe diſpoſition that I could not be ſatisfied without Chriſt, ſo that I ſaid within my ſelfe, give me a Chriſt or I dy: and the <hi>diſpoſition</hi> to beleeving I found very <hi>difficult</hi> and hard, when God ſet me upon it; a work too hard for me, without the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of an <hi>Omnipotent</hi> God; which <note place="margin">The way of obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</note> made me the more eagarly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue it, at the hands of him who was able to give it; God (when his ſet time was come) wrought every <hi>diſpoſition</hi> in me ſutable to the grace that hee was about to convey to my Soule; and then I ſaw nothing in any thing either in <hi>heaven</hi> or earth that could doe me good but the revealing <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> to my Soule. Duties would not <hi>juſtify,</hi> no; <hi>inherent grace</hi> was no <hi>Iuſtification</hi> in it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:184283:27"/> ſelfe, though a fruit of <hi>Iuſtification</hi> yet no cauſe of it. <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> was the <hi>all in all</hi> both for <hi>Sanctification</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. laſt.</note> and <hi>Iuſtification;</hi> and there I ſaw a way to make uſe of Chriſt by way of <hi>Iuſtification;</hi> I ſaw more fully then before <hi>that all my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe was imperfect,</hi> but in Chriſt it was <hi>compleate:</hi> when the love of God was thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to my Soule, then it did <hi>conſtraine</hi> me to work out of a <hi>higher principle</hi> then before; I thought with my ſelfe, were there no <hi>hell</hi> to puniſh, nor <hi>Heaven</hi> to reward, yet there was <hi>comfort</hi> enough in <hi>God,</hi> and in the <hi>refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">A Goſpell-ſpirit.</note> of his <hi>ſpirit</hi> to carry me on in a way of <hi>obedience</hi> to his gracious, and holy <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Commands;</hi> and then though I had matter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough within my ſelfe, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne my ſelf by reaſon that grace which in me was weak, my fleſh
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:184283:27"/> being full of all <hi>imperfections,</hi> yet I knew all was made up in Chriſts <hi>perfection.</hi> I made uſe of the Law for a rule to <hi>walk</hi> by, not expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Her opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Law, and of thoſe that reject it.</note> to <hi>fullfill</hi> it; So that the law muſt have <hi>Dominion</hi> over a man (for a rule) as long as he liveth: who ſo caſts the Law of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind his back, ſurely hath not partaken ſo far as I can conjecture of the <hi>ſaving grace</hi> of God; and this I ſaw, that Chriſt came not to <hi>deſtroy</hi> the law, but to <hi>fullfill</hi> it; Chriſt is the <hi>end of the law to every one that beleeveth;</hi> we are not to throw it by, as of no uſe, but in what we fall ſhort, to make uſe of him, that is of Chriſt to make it up: the more I made uſe of the Law, the more I ſaw that it was <hi>holy, juſt, and good. For wee ſhould not walke as doe others (as men</hi> without a rule;) there is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite cauſe, that we ſhould look
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184283:28"/> to our Lords <hi>Commandement,</hi> as Chriſt kept the Commands when hee was upon earth, ſo doubtleſſe he would have his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple keep them; when we have ſuch a bleſſed <hi>Mediator</hi> to ſtand up in the gap if in any thing the <note place="margin">Chriſtians engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to keep the Law.</note> law condemns us, he ſteps in, and undertakes for us, he gave full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for the condemning po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of it; but hath left the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal part of it for us to make uſe of. I was troubled with in my ſelf, if at any time I thought any thought, <note place="margin">A watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and zealous frame of Spirit.</note> or did any deed, contrary to the command of God; yea how hath my Soule been grieved becauſe other men kept not the law of God?</p>
                     <p>I found the actings of God <hi>in</hi> me and <hi>toward</hi> me, I prayed in another manner then before, that <note place="margin">Her ſenſe of God.</note> when I askt any thing for my ſelfe or others, <hi>agreeable</hi> to Gods will,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:184283:28"/> eſpecially in ſtraights, I found a holy <hi>boldneſſe</hi> and <hi>confidence</hi> that God would anſwer, and he did anſwer abundantly beyond what I can expreſſe, not becauſe of my <hi>requeſt,</hi> but becauſe <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Her experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her prayer, and her right conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and uſe of it.</note> 
                        <hi>interceded;</hi> he took my broken, and imperfect <hi>requeſts,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſhattered expreſsions,</hi> and preſented them blameleſſe before God; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I <hi>prayed,</hi> but becauſe he <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted</hi> to ſhew mercy; and ſo <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged</hi> and <hi>incouraged</hi> me to wait upon him, in his ſervice.</p>
                     <p>My ſoule can teſtify, I have had as much from God, in the way of that ordinance, as any: I have been filled as full of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, by God in that ordinance, <note place="margin">A rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</note> as my ſoule could poſſibly attaine unto; I never wanted any thing for my ſelfe, or others, but I went to God for; there was none grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in heaven, or earth, I could
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184283:29"/> reſort unto; I find him to be a fountaine never drawne dry; oh! that none would goe to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne when there is ſo much in the Fountain! To looke at Ciſternes <note place="margin">The uſe of Ciſternes.</note> as they are in themſelves, they are nothing, but they may be made uſe of to Gods glory; when uſed by God, and lookt at <hi>through</hi> God the Fountaine, whatever is done by the creature God doth (but by a <hi>ſecondary</hi> meanes;) So that it is <hi>in,</hi> and from the Lord, that we have all that we injoy; and when God brought me to the bed of <hi>affliction,</hi> then he was pleaſed to make a <hi>report</hi> a new of all that he had done for my ſoule, which made my heart to <hi>burne</hi> within me in <hi>love</hi> to God, and <note place="margin">Sweet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> with deſire to make known to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers how <hi>good</hi> the Lord was to my ſoule; all his dealings with mee to <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>body</hi> I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:184283:29"/> are in much <hi>love;</hi> ſo that the place I found <hi>experimentally</hi> true, Rom. 8. 28. Gods gracious <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 28.</note> diſpenſation in fitting me for <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction</hi> was exceeding great; ſo that I may ſay with Job <hi>that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing came upon me but the thing I feared.</hi> God was pleaſed to tell mee what he was about to doe, and that in a way of anſwer to prayer. I could conclude as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently that <hi>affliction</hi> ſhould come, as if it had been upon me already; and God gave me a ſtrong <hi>reſolution</hi> to abide his <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> whatever it was: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome time of <hi>prayer</hi> he gave a promiſe ſutable to the condition he was about to bring upon me, the promiſe was, <hi>happy is the man whom thou correcteſt, &amp;c.</hi> And he hath taught me four things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <note place="margin">Four things ſutable to an afflicted condition.</note> and ſutable to every afflicted condition whatever. The firſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:184283:30"/> 
                        <hi>is to eye the hand of God in the affliction;</hi> for the ſeeing the hand of God made mee ſilent in his preſence, and made me willing to ſubmit to him. The ſecond thing was, that <hi>he ſhewed me his face</hi> and <hi>preſence,</hi> which is <hi>better than life.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>He brought off my will to ſubmit to him,</hi> as to a <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> from many ſpeciall places of divine writ. Fourthly, <hi>He made me more than in an ordinary way to</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Gods graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dealing with her in relation to Affliction. 4 Ends of Affliction apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by her.</note> 
                        <hi>drawe nigh to God,</hi> to know why hee did contend with mee; one end was for <hi>ſin;</hi> ſin hath a being, though not a reigning power in me, for which cauſe I have cauſe to lay low. A ſecond end was for <hi>exerciſe of faith</hi> and <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>other graces.</hi> A third end was that I might have <hi>liberty</hi> to take occaſion to make a report to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers what God hath done for my ſoule, that by this meanes, I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184283:30"/> might bring ſome honour to God. A fourth end was, <hi>that I might be ſet</hi> upon that <hi>evangelicall worke of ſetting forth the high prayſes of God;</hi> which work though I could do it to the utmoſt here, yet its no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to what ſhall be in heaven: And therefore I deſire to bleſſe God that there is an <hi>eternity</hi> to praiſe him in. In my affliction God hath verified many places of Scriptures which I ſee to be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally</hi> true that I did not ſee before; ſo that I am conſtrained to ſay oft, and againe, <hi>What am</hi> I? and <hi>what is my fathers houſe? that the Lord ſhould bring me hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto?</hi> and with David, <hi>Lord what is man that thou art mindfull of him, or the ſonne of man that thou ſhouldeſt viſit him.</hi> Another <note place="margin">Mercy in judgment.</note> thing I have obſerved in my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, <hi>that God hath wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully chayned up Satan in this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</hi> He was never let looſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:184283:31"/> me but twice in all my afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: he came forth often like a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but in a <hi>chaine,</hi> roaring for his prey; but God ſtopt his mouth, that he could get no do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over me. Thoſe two times he was let looſe, The firſt time was about my <hi>ſpirituall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:</hi> he would have troubled me with three things, as he did Chriſt by queries; Firſt <hi>how I knew that I was a child of God,</hi> And ſecondly <hi>how I could make out my interest in Christ,</hi> whether it it was fancy or <hi>deluſion</hi> or whether <hi>reall:</hi> Next thirdly he would have <note place="margin">Her ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth againſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</note> perſwaded me that I laye under the guilt of ſome ſinne, that was not pardoned; my anſwer was to the firſt, I knew I was a child of God, by his <hi>Word &amp; Works</hi> God made it out to me: to the ſecond I anſwered, <hi>that God had aſſured me of an intereſt in Chriſt, by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the ſpirit, bearing witneſſe</hi>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:184283:31"/> 
                        <hi>with abundance of of conſolation that I was his ſpouſe: thy maker is thine huſband &amp;c.</hi> To the third I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>God pardoned all ſinnes in reſpect of himſelfe at once.</hi> I only did lye under the guilt of ſome ſins, but God came in abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a promiſe that God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted me from all. And ſo Satans objection was fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; and I abundandly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Another temptation was about the time of Gods taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my neare <hi>relation</hi> which was a <hi>ſiſter</hi> of mine, he took an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by the weakneſſe of my body oftentimes to trouble me with many <hi>thoughts</hi> of her death, and the manner of it, (both ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and waking) and I was in ſome queſtion about her <hi>eternall</hi> condition: at firſt I thought it was rather ſome peece of Nature than any temptation; but as ſoone
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184283:32"/> as I ſaw it was a <hi>temptation,</hi> I ſet my ſelfe to ſeek God againſt it; And I had this <hi>anſwer</hi> from God, after a few thoughts, in ſeeking, that the Lord would <hi>rebuke the devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer for my bodies ſake;</hi> and from this ſcripture that <hi>the God of Satan would bruiſe Satan under my feet ſhortly:</hi> and for my ſiſters <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and the manner of her <hi>death,</hi> God gave this word, <hi>Is thy eye evill becauſe mine is good? ſhall I not doe with mine owne what I will;</hi> aye (ſaid my ſoul) if ſhe were his, I could be the better perſwaded to give her up to God; then God told me, <hi>he lookt not as man lookt;</hi> but if there <hi>were any work of God he would owne his owne work,</hi> but however he cauſed me to leave her <note place="margin">Her ſtoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Gods ſoveraignty</note> to his <hi>prerogative royall</hi> who <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth righteous Iudgement.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I ſaw a neceſſity of frequenting the beſt <hi>meanes:</hi> once in ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:184283:32"/> I ſaw <hi>abundance</hi> from God, to <note place="margin">Her care to honour her Parents in what ſhe might, with ſecurity to her conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> incourage me in that way: my <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Mother</hi> commanded me to goe one way to hear, and I was put upon it, to goe another <hi>way,</hi> for which they were very fierce and violent, the Lord was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to put me upon it, to inquire what I ſhould doe in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and while I was thinking, the fifth commandement came into my thoughts, <hi>honour your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, &amp;c.</hi> Then I began to Thinke what <hi>honour</hi> was due to them, being deſirous to give them that <hi>honour</hi> that I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; if they commanded with God, I was ready and willing to obey them, with cherefulneſſe: but ſeeing they commanded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God, I ſaw the <hi>command</hi> of God <hi>greater</hi> than their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: and I went to the word, and God met me there, in ſuch a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:184283:33"/> way that he gave me <hi>incouragement</hi> to goe through <hi>oppoſition</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficulty</hi> in time to come, whatever I ſhould meet withall (though they were ſtripes) I was willing to give my <hi>back to the ſmiters,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to give up my <hi>conſcience</hi> to be racked; the oppoſition of the creature is not much when Gods makes it eaſy. This &amp; other <hi>experiences</hi> I have had of Gods <hi>power</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> in a way <note place="margin">Her reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſſe for God.</note> where I met with <hi>oppoſition:</hi> So that its good to be <hi>reſolute</hi> for God; though you may loſe ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with the creature, yet yee ſhall be double gayners if you may injoy the favour of God: <hi>the light of his countenance is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than life.</hi> The next thing I ſaw was, that there was a <hi>faith</hi> which was according to <hi>ſight,</hi> like that of <hi>Thomas, He beleeved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaw:</hi> and another <hi>faith</hi>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:184283:33"/> 
                        <hi>beyond ſight,</hi> which was to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve upon the ſight of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of grace plentifully upon my ſoule. When God withdrew the ſence of his love, ſo that I did not injoy the dayly <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes</hi> of Gods love, I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to live upon the <hi>immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Strong Faith.</note> 
                        <hi>and unchangableneſſe of God.</hi> Notwitwſtanding the great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and favour of God formerly convayed, I was conſtrained with David to cry out, <hi>Reſtore</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">A deſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                        <hi>to me the joy of thy ſalvation;</hi> and then I apprehended that Chriſt was abſent, at which time I lived <hi>ſolitary,</hi> and in the <hi>Darke.</hi> I lookt <note place="margin">Her carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in it.</note> upon Chriſt as a husband, but yet as a husband going a Journey, and hid behind a curtaine, ſo that my ſoule was as the ſpouſe <hi>reſtleſſe</hi> in looking out to <hi>inquire</hi> after him: but in time he ſent many love letters to me which were theſe,</p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:184283:34"/>
                     <p> 
                        <hi>To you that feare my name, ſhall the</hi> Sunne <hi>of righteouſneſſe ariſe with healing in his wings:</hi> Though I did not feare him perfectly and as I ought, yet I had ſome deſires to ſerve him in truth. And another was, <hi>Hee that ſhall come, will come, and will not ſtay;</hi> yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time by reaſon of his abſence I wondred what my temper was, and ſaid, what is God about to teach me? oh that I knew his mind! and I would doe it; oh that I knew what my preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition were! and in time God graciouſly came in with this ſcripture, and perſwaded me with <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20.</note> Paul, <hi>that the life I now lived</hi> was by <hi>the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelfe</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</note> 
                        <hi>for me.</hi> And <hi>that his grace was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Her reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very out of her deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                        <hi>for me:</hi> and at laſt I ſaw him (behind the curtaines) I ſaw him
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184283:34"/> but could not <hi>injoy</hi> him: at laſt I found him whom my ſoule loved.</p>
                     <p>God hath not ſet me a preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, in reſpect of my bodily affliction, but he hath cauſed me not to repine againſt him, if he make me a preſident to others; ſo I may be ſerviceable and be made inſtrumentall for the good of any poore ſoule, my ſoule is ſatisfied, <note place="margin">Her ſweet Goſpell-ſpirit in her ſad Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> and I am abundantly willing to ſubmit, ſo God may be glorified, and any poore ſoule edified: it is ſatisfaction enough to me, ſo I may be an inſtrument in Gods hand for any ſpirituall good. The paths of God are pleaſant paths, I could wiſh it were more and more <hi>my meat and drink to doe the will of my father.</hi> I feare more that too much <hi>impatience</hi> ſhould break forth for an earneſt <hi>deſire for heaven,</hi> than any thing:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:184283:35"/> for I found ſome deceit in my heart, in that particular, break out once, And I have cauſe to feare there is more of the fire, if the Lord doe not quench it. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once in my owne apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and in the ſight of many beholders at the point of death, not expecting to live many dayes, I apprehended God ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Her impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of ſtaying here.</note> forth two meſſengers, the one was the grim ſerjeant <hi>Death</hi> with a commiſſion from God to areſt the body: I apprehended that the <hi>reſt</hi> of the body ſhould but ſet the ſoule at liberty. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meſſenger ſent from God was the Angell of God with a commiſſion from God to carry the ſoule to the place of <hi>Iuſt men made perfect,</hi> ſo that I was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to bid <hi>adue</hi> to all creature<hi>-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements,</hi> onely <hi>I was to work while it was called to day, the</hi>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:184283:35"/> 
                        <hi>works of God, for the night was at hand when I ſhould no more work with the Saints on earth.</hi> It was ſuch a refreſhment to my ſoule, that my time was at hand, that I was glad to be <hi>uncloathed</hi> that I might be <hi>cloathed upon.</hi> So that I could ſay, <hi>oh death where is thy ſting?</hi> oh hell where is thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</p>
                     <p>I was taken up much 2 or 3 <note place="margin">Her care to dye to the Lord.</note> dayes in the work of exhortation of friends that came to viſit me; then the Lord ſent a meſſenger of his who made a new <hi>report</hi> again of my <hi>Fathers</hi> houſe, which was much illuſtrated to me by an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his. I could not but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe to them who came to viſit me what great things were to be injoyed in my <hi>fathers houſe,</hi> &amp; ſaid, oh! that they might come to me: and to the Inſtrument I ſaid; if God had ſent him to make a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi>
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:184283:36"/> of theſe things to my eares, I bid him ſpeake on: for I was willing to heare what God would ſpeake to me by him. I was much converſant in the <hi>meditation</hi> of theſe things for twenty four houres or there about: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was out of heaven in my thoughts, I felt a <hi>thorue in my fleſh,</hi> Satan buffeting of me, arguing thus againſt Gods proceedings, by reaſon of the diſpenſation of God changing my bodily condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, promiſing me ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance <hi>in the Land of the living for a ſeaſon:</hi> here I found the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of the fleſh with the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Satan to quarell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, being unwilling to <hi>abide in the fleſh,</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>God ſaw it was better for me to be in the body for a time.</hi> I deſire what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <note place="margin">A ſweet frame of ſpirit.</note> ſeem good to God may not ſeeme grievous to me. I had no
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184283:36"/> quiet nor reſt in my ſoul till I ſaw this diſtemper (my unwillingnes to ſubmit to the wil of God) wrought out, and for that the Lord made me to ſeeke him <hi>earneſtly,</hi> and he was found in the day of my <hi>affliction;</hi> I ſaid within my ſelf, <hi>what good would my life doe me;</hi> if God did not take away the evill of ſin? my affliction was nothing, but my ſin was my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction; and the Lord <hi>harkned and heard,</hi> and took away my <hi>ſin,</hi> &amp; then I found my affliction nothing; though greater than formerly, yet <note place="margin">Affliction eaſie.</note> as eaſie as ever: then the Lord put me upon it to conſider, why he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid his coming, in that way wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I apprehended he was about to <hi>Come,</hi> &amp; I apprehended theſe to be the ends. Firſt, <hi>To let me ſee the evill</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Her holy interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her.</note> 
                        <hi>of my heart,</hi> what I was in my ſelfe, refractory &amp; rebellious; &amp; another end was, that I might ſee the worke of Gods grace in the hearts of ſome,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:184283:37"/> and be inſtrumentall to doe ſome thing for their good (if God plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to incline me) for the helping forward of that work of his: for I apprehend I ſhall work no more for the Saints after this life; though Ieſus Chriſt worke for the Saints in Heaven, as well as when he was on earth, yet the Saints work for the Saints only in this life. The other end was (as I apprehend) that I might live to take care for a Child; and to engage ſome honeſt man to take him; which is partly effected. Another end (I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend) was that I might take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the anſwer of the prayers of others.</p>
                     <p>Againe, having been taken up in my thoughts more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in and about the differences of the times among the Saints, in theſe late yeares, in, and about
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:184283:37"/> ſome Circumſtances about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as I apprehend; and I <note place="margin">Her opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the differences of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time.</note> was perſwaded that the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance was nothing, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the ſubſtance: ſome ſaid this was the way, and ſome ſaid <hi>that was the way:</hi> ſome were for a ſeparated Church, others for a mixt Church. Firſt this I was perſwaded, <hi>that Ieſus Chriſt was the only way to ſalvation, by a worke of grace in the hearts of his people.</hi> But I apprehending that the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Gods people was very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and that thoſe of the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſociety, as they are called, did make an improvement of the ſociety of the Saints, more than thoſe that were out of that way did for the preſent; It made me to have ſome inclination to that way, and thereupon to apply my ſelfe to God for his direction in it what to doe; then I ſaw that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:184283:38"/> the <hi>Independent ſociety</hi> went into their <hi>way</hi> in and by a <hi>covenant,</hi> which I could not ſee any ground for: whereupon I deſired their grounds, but found little or no ſatisfaction. Their ſcriptures were Exod. 19. 6. Ezek. 16. 6, 7, 8. Jer. 50. 5. Acts 5. 13. Eph. 4. 3. <hi>Be</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 6, 7, 8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50. 5. <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Epeſ.</hi> 4. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>knit together in love,</hi> which ſay they, implies a covenant: but I could not ſee by <hi>their light,</hi> but did apprehend that that ſcripture was directed to the <hi>Saints in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> and not to <hi>Congregations</hi> in particular: then they ſaid they preſt not their covenant as abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <note place="margin">Her opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into Church-fellowſhip by a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note> 
                        <hi>neceſſary,</hi> but left it as a <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary act;</hi> then I began to think whether a <hi>voluntary vow</hi> were lawfull to be taken in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> which I find lawfull in ſcripture; as <hi>David</hi> did <hi>vow</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſin; and its put upon <hi>record</hi> in ſcripture, that <hi>if we vow</hi>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:184283:38"/> 
                        <hi>to God we muſt not deferr to pay it:</hi> then I began to think that the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Gods people was <hi>vſefull;</hi> and if it could not be injoyed <note place="margin">Note.</note> without <hi>covenanting,</hi> its juſt with God to give us up to <hi>covenanting</hi> for the <hi>hardneſſe of our hearts,</hi> who would not willingly do it without this. And I conceive that <hi>David</hi> could not come up to duty as he would till he came to <hi>covenanting;</hi> but I began to think wheher this <hi>covenant</hi> ſo much preſt was my duty, viz. <hi>to joyne in a way of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for the injoyment of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the Saints;</hi> and after ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, he gave me this place. <hi>If thou doeſt not vow thou doeſt not</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Her deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination upon it.</note> 
                        <hi>ſin;</hi> and it ſatisfied me that I might injoy the ſociety with the Saints out of the way, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaw no neceſſity of ingaging my ſelfe in the way.</p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:184283:39"/>
                     <p> And he alſo gave me theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to ſatisfie me further, <hi>be ye followers of me as I am of Chriſt,</hi> That is, in this, that <hi>I deſire to know nothing but Ieſus Chriſt, and him crucified,</hi> and this Scripture, <hi>this is eternall life, to know God, and Ieſus Chriſt, whom thou haſt ſent,</hi> and this of the Apoſtle, <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren have fellowſhip with us,</hi> for <hi>truly we have fellowſhip with the Father and the Son the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Then I could not but break forth into bleſſing of God, that I have had much <hi>fellowſhip with the ſonne the Lord Ieſus,</hi> and as much as God hath ſeene good for me with the Saints: ſo that I have cauſe to bleſſe God, and to truſt in God who hath given me ſociety with the Saints, out of the way, as much as in the way: ſo that that which God gives is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:184283:39"/> not in reference to the way; but to his owne love: I ſee nothing in the way, but what hath been injoyed out of the way: and therefore not to be ſo much lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up, as it hath been and is by ſome.</p>
                     <p>I pray God that while others ingage themſelves by covenant, to watch over ſo many ſoules in a congregation (which is a great work) they be not to negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in watching over themſelves.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184283:40"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:184283:40"/>
                  <p> THE LIFE &amp; DEATH OF A true CHRISTIAN: Deciphered in a Sermon Preached upon the 14 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6, 7 Verſ. At the <hi>Buriall</hi> of <hi>Mary Simpſon;</hi> a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious young Maid, lately li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the City of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BY JOHN COLLINGS, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts, and Preacher of Gods Word to <hi>Saviours</hi> Pariſh in the ſaid City.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>2 Cor. Ch. 5. v. 2.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For in this we groan earneſtly, deſiring to be cloathed upon with our houſe which is from heaven.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <bibl>Verſe 3.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If ſo that being cloathed, we bee not found naked.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rich. Tomlins.</hi> 1649.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184283:41"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184283:41"/>
                  <head>The Life and Death of <hi>a true Christian.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>Rom. 14. ver. 7, 8.</bibl>
                     <q>For none of us liveth to himſelfe; And no man dies to himſelfe; but whether we live we live unto the Lord, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we dye, we dye unto the Lord: Whether therefore we live or dye, we are the Lords.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the <hi>Author</hi> of this Epiſtle, none is ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant but knowes it is <hi>Paul.</hi> It was written to the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Romans.</hi> For the ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, it is an Elaborate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, clearing up the Doctrine
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:184283:42"/> of <hi>Iuſtification;</hi> that's the ſubject of the doctrinall part of it, in the eleven firſt chapters: the enſuing part of it is more <hi>practicall,</hi> in which the Apoſtle gives ſeverall precepts to the beleeving <hi>Romans,</hi> whether in <hi>publicke Offices</hi> or in private <hi>relations,</hi> Inſtructing them how to carry themſelves towards God, and each towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>In this Chapter he inſtructs them how to demeane them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves towards their <hi>diſſenting weak brethren.</hi> In thoſe primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, there were ſome Chriſtians that were ſtumbled at the preſent <hi>abrogation of the ceremoniall law,</hi> and were not ſo fully as others inſtructed in the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſtian liberty,</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by the comming, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Upon this, from the too rigid
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184283:42"/> Cenſoriouſneſſe of other Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians, there grew a diviſion, and (as I am apt to beleeve) a <hi>ſeparation</hi> in the Church: It ſeemeth the ſtumble was concerning two points of the ceremoniall law; Firſt, The <hi>eating of meats Vnclean</hi> by the law: Secondly, the other, the <hi>Obſervation of ſuch dayes as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Iewiſh law were to be kept holy.</hi> Thoſe Chriſtians that were well inſtructed in the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the <hi>liberty</hi> purchaſed by Jeſus Chriſt from thoſe <hi>Iewiſh ceremonies,</hi> rightly conceived, that Firſt, Thoſe beaſts which were <hi>Vncleane to the Iews</hi> were <hi>not</hi> now <hi>Vncleane:</hi> It was ſince then that God had given leave to <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>kill</hi> and <hi>eate,</hi> with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to him, to call nothing <hi>Common or Vncleane</hi> which he had <hi>ſanctified.</hi> And I conceive that piece of the Ceremonall law did
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184283:43"/> typifie the Uncleaneneſſe of the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> till the <hi>Partition wall</hi> was pulled downe; and 2. They knew that under the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> Chriſtians were by no morall precept engaged to keep any day <hi>holy</hi> but the Lords day: yet the other Chriſtians not ſeeing with ſo cleare a light, as they ſaw, durſt not doe theſe things, but ſtill perſiſted in abſtaining from ſome <hi>meats,</hi> and the <hi>obſervation of ſome holy dayes,</hi> which needed not, had they been but well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed. But as the conſciences of theſe were too <hi>ſcrupulous</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious;</hi> So the ſpirits of the other were too <hi>rigid</hi> and <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious,</hi> preſently upon this to refuſe <hi>communion</hi> with them. The Apoſtle therefore in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter writes to them, to mind them how to carry themſelves towards their weak brethren.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184283:43"/> Firſt, He gives a generall precept, To <hi>receive</hi> them: but wiſely, <hi>Not to doubtful diſputations:</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatively, <note place="margin">Through the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their faith.</note> v. 2. <hi>not to deſpiſe them: we ought not to deſpiſe but brotherly to Receive thoſe that differ not from us in fundamentals though they cannot agree with us in circumſtantialls.</hi> For I conceive that the difference was not here a thing indifferent, it was utterly <hi>unlawfull,</hi> and <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious</hi> to keep Jewiſh holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes by vertue of an obligation from the Ceremoniall law. It was unlawfull for them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thoſe creatures <hi>Common or uncleane</hi> which the Lord had <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified,</hi> yet ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>be tender of them.</hi> Firſt, deſpiſe them not. Secondly, <hi>puzzle them not in doubtful diſputations.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>do not judge or condemne them.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Receive them,</hi> into your hearts by <hi>love</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>affection</hi> toward
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184283:44"/> them; Into your Congregations not refuſing <hi>communion</hi> with them. Now having given them this generall Leſſon of Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he preſſeth it in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing verſes, by ſeverall Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; The firſt is laid downe <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>God hath Received him:</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him, how? he hath loved his ſoule in Jeſus Chriſt, and <hi>united</hi> him to himſelf; will ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject whom God receiveth? doth God think him worthy of his heart, and doe not you think him worthy of yours? will God receive him to everlaſting <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> with himſelfe, and is he not worthy to be received into the <hi>Communion</hi> of your Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Secondly, <hi>from the very law of Nature; who art thou that con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demneſt another mans ſervant? he ſtands, or fals to his own maſter.</hi> This is ſpoken to diſſwade them from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184283:44"/> cenſuring or judging; why ſaith the Apoſtle, he is Gods <hi>ſervant</hi> not yours, who bids you judge him? leave him to his owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and doe not you exerciſe a rigid unwarrantable Maſtery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him. Thirdly, <hi>from the love of God to him, Yea he ſhall be establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</hi> God that hath ſhined in with ſome light of knowledge, and faith, into him, will in his due time (ſaith the Apoſtle) ſhine with more; that though he ſeemes to be now weak, yet he ſhall be ſtrong; though he be a little ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering, now for the preſent, yet he ſhall be ſetled, and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; and this is proved from the two ſtrongeſt Arguments in the world; to aſſure to a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian the accompliſhing of any promiſe for the carrying on any work of grace. Firſt, <hi>Gods power.</hi> v. 4. <hi>He is able to make him ſtand.</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:184283:45"/> Secondly, <hi>Gods love,</hi> he will doe to his utmoſt for him, <hi>he ſhall be establiſhed.</hi> The word is <hi>paſſive</hi> to denote the freeneſſe of Gods act in it.</p>
                  <p>A fourth Argument is drawne <hi>from the joint deſigne that theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Chriſtians (and that in this very buſineſſe) carried on with thoſe whoſe Spirits were more cleare in the thing,</hi> viz. <hi>The glory of God,</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if they were ſuch baſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wretches, as kept up theſe ceremonies out of a ſuperſtitious humour, Holy dayes meerly to <hi>eat,</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> in, and riſe up to <hi>play</hi> in, to be dayes of prophanneſſe, &amp;c. or if they kept up theſe meerly to diſturbe the Church of Chriſt, or to deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, then it were ſomething; but being the caſe is ſo, that they are ſuch perſons as truly aime at the <hi>glory</hi> of God in this action,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184283:45"/> and diſſent becauſe they are not yet fully convinced that they are freed from theſe ceremonies; and think they ſhould diſhonour God in diſobeying his command, if they ſhould not; <hi>Beare with them.</hi> Yea (may ſome ſay) but how ſhould we know this?</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the Apoſtle proves it, 1. <hi>From the manner of their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of theſe dayes, and eating theſe meats.</hi> 1. They obſerved them to the Lord. They ate to the Lord, <hi>giving God thanks:</hi> they did not barely obſerve the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> but with a great deale of <hi>holineſſe,</hi> that the ſhell and the kernell went together.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, he proveth it, from the generall ſcope, and aime of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very true Chriſtian both in his life and death. <hi>For none of us liveth to himſelf, &amp;c.</hi> They are ſome of <hi>us</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) true beleevers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184283:46"/> in whom the grace of God dwells. Now</p>
                  <q>None of us liveth to himſelfe, and No man dieth to himſelfe. For whether we live we live unto the Lord, and whether we die we die unto the Lord: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we live therefore or die we are the Lords.</q>
                  <p>Thus I have brought you to my text, which is a ſhort Account of a Chriſtians <hi>Pilgrimage.</hi> The life and death of a Saint. In it conſider</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>The particular of a Chriſtians Life</hi> and <hi>Death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>The Summa totalis of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The particular of it is ſet down, firſt, <hi>Negativè; None of us liveth to himſelfe, and no man dieth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Affirmativè; Whether we live we live unto the Lord, and whether we die we die unto the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:184283:46"/>
                  <p> Then there's the Totall ſumme, <hi>Whether therefore we live or die we are the Lords.</hi> Or if you pleaſe, Here's the doctrine, <hi>No beleever lives to himſelfe, nor dies to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but if he lives, he lives to the Lord, and if he dies, he dies to the Lord.</hi> Secondly, Here is an <hi>Inference</hi> from the Doctrine, a Conſolatory Application: <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therefore we live or dy we are the Lords.</hi> Or (as a learned Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentator <note place="margin">Pareus ad locum.</note> well notes) heres a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Doctrine, why we ſhould in our life live unto the Lord, and in our death dye unto the Lord: Becauſe in life and death <hi>we are the Lords.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is no great matter difficult in the words, that which is to be opened about them, I ſhall open in the Doctrine. And that I may contract all as ſhort as may be, I ſhall ſumme up both the verſes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184283:47"/> in this one Propoſition of Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</p>
                  <q>Doct. <hi>That all beleevers, who while they live, live not to themſelves, and if they dye, dye not to themſelves, but whiles they live, they live to the Lord, and when they dye, they dye to the Lord, whether they live, or dye are the Lords: and becauſe in life or death, they are the Lords, It is their duty not to live, nor dye to themſelves, but to live and dye to the Lord.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>It is large, but eaſy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, becauſe in the words of the text. For my better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in the handling of it, and for the helping of your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I ſhall branch the doctrine into theſe four particulars which I will handle diſtinctly, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply joyntly.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:184283:47"/>
                     <item>1. <hi>That the beleever in his life is the Lords.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>That becauſe of it, he ought not to live to himſelfe but to the Lord.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>That when he dyes he dyes not to himſelfe but unto God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>That in death he alſo is and ſhall be the Lords.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <p>Firſt of the firſt. 1. <hi>That the true beleever in his life is the Lords.</hi> I ſhal open it, and ſhew you in what reſpects, and prove the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars as I paſſe them by, ſhortly. I ſhall open it but in three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, 1. <hi>He is the Lords by purchaſe.</hi> 2. <hi>He is the Lords by Poſſeſsion.</hi> 3. <hi>He is the Lords by neare Relation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Firſt of all, <hi>He is the Lords</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">The Lords Purchaſe.</note> 
                        <hi>by purchaſe,</hi> and a deare purchaſe; <hi>he hath purchaſed them with his owne blood.</hi> Acts 20. 28. The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that hath had a painefull travell ſayes to the child, A
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184283:48"/> deare child thou haſt been to me, and <hi>Zipporah</hi> to <hi>Moſes, ſurely a bloody husband haſt thou been to me.</hi> God may ſay, Bellevers! Children! you have been deare Children, bloody children unto me, you have coſt me my owne heart blood, a great ranſome! They are called <hi>the Purchaſed poſſeſsion.</hi> Eph. 1. 14. And a dear purchaſe too that coſt the owners heart blood. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſpeak truth, doe you not think you coſt Chriſt more then ye are worth, bodyes and ſcules, and all? It is true to purpoſe too that the Apoſtle ſayes. 1 Cor. 6. 20. <hi>For ye are bought with a price, therefore, &amp;c.</hi> a <hi>price</hi> indeed yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſilver nor gold</hi> (of that Chriſt had none,) <hi>but what he had he gave</hi> you, and gave for you, even his own <hi>life</hi> for a ranſome for the ſins of many; never was there ſo deare a <hi>bargaine,</hi> and yet never fewer
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184283:48"/> 
                        <hi>words</hi> ſpent about one. He bought them of the <hi>Father.</hi> Joh. 10. 29. and Joh. 17. Indeed there it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>giving,</hi> but he gave his <hi>blood</hi> for them: and yet there was an act of <hi>grace</hi> in the Father giving the <hi>Elect</hi> to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> It is true, you may ſay, that they were the <hi>Devills Captives.</hi> Eph. 2. v. 2, 3. But I anſwer, that the <hi>Devill</hi> was but Gods <hi>jayler,</hi> hee keeps them by nature in a <hi>Captivity,</hi> but it is for a debt due to the <hi>Fathers juſtice.</hi> Now God gave them to Chriſt paying ſuch a <hi>price.</hi> One would wonder to think, he ſhould med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with ſo hard, and <hi>unprofitable</hi> a <hi>bargaine,</hi> but yet he did, and with ſuch <hi>alacrity</hi> that there was ſcarce too <hi>words</hi> betwixt his <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>him</hi> about it. The <hi>Father</hi> writ downe in his book, <hi>If you will have them thats the price, you ſhall goe, and doe my will (which is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:184283:49"/> 
                        <hi>upon you their nature)</hi> Suffering, Dying, &amp;c. Chriſt preſently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed <hi>Done:</hi> and by ſuch a day it ſhall be all paid, Pſal. 40. v. 7. Heb. 10. 8. <hi>In the Volume of thy book it is written of me. Lo! I come to doe thy will, O God!</hi> There ſhall no more words be made of it (ſaith Chriſt) I will doe it: Thus there was a <hi>Covenant ſtroke,</hi> betwixt the Father and the Son for <hi>The purchaſed poſſeſsion.</hi> Thus they are the Lords by Purchaſe. <hi>Pretium Sanguinis,</hi> the price of his owne deare heart blood.</p>
                     <p>They are the Lords <hi>Poſſeſsion:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 3. Eph. 2. 22. Tit. 2. 14. 1 Cor. 3. 17.</note> They are his owne, he calls them his <hi>heritage,</hi> his <hi>habitation,</hi> his <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people,</hi> The <hi>ſheep of his paſture,</hi> The <hi>ſheep of his flock,</hi> The <hi>temple of God.</hi> His title to them I cleared before, but not altogether. All title you know is either, 1. By <hi>inheritance,</hi> or 2. By <hi>purchaſe,</hi>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:184283:49"/> or 3. By <hi>gift.</hi> God hath every of theſe wayes a title to belevers. 1. By purchaſe. So I have already cleared Chriſts title to beleevers: I ſhewed you, 1. Of whom he bought this <hi>poſſeſsion.</hi> 2. <hi>Out of whoſe hands.</hi> 3. <hi>What he paid for it.</hi> But you know if a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract with another for a houſe or ground, and after ſuch a contract pay the price for which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts with him that hath the ſale in his power: yet after all this he muſt have <hi>poſſeſsion</hi> given him, and then it is fully and moſt properly called his own. Beleevers are the Lord Chriſts thus; he hath not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>contracted</hi> for them, and <hi>paid his full price,</hi> but he hath alſo taken <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and ſeiſiu</hi> of them. Joh. 10. 29. <hi>The father hath given</hi> them to him: and Joh. 17. <hi>Of all that thou haſt given me I have loſt none.</hi> And now they are his <hi>inheritance,</hi>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:184283:50"/> he hath the <hi>fee ſimple</hi> of all his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> ones, and by his 1. <hi>Aſſuming</hi> their fleſh hath taken <hi>livery,</hi> and <hi>ſeiſin</hi> of their natures. 2. <hi>Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Vniting himſelfe unto them,</hi> he hath brought himſelfe and his furniture for his houſe, all the graces of his holy ſpirit, to dwell in them; nay they are his <hi>peculiar</hi> Manſion in whom he delights to <hi>dwell: you have I knowne (ſaith he) above all the Nations of the Earth:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Amos 3. 2.</note> though all the world be mine, and I can pitch my <hi>tent</hi> any where, and dwell in my owne too, yet <hi>you only I have knowne;</hi> you are the <hi>Manſion-</hi>houſe which I ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for my glory; where I will come and keep houſe my ſelfe in perſon. They are the Lords poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion: thats the ſecond.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. They are the Lords <hi>by neare Relation.</hi> Neare relations are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily by way of appropriation
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184283:50"/> called ours; <hi>wives,</hi> and <hi>children,</hi> and <hi>ſervants;</hi> we ſay of ſuch a woman, or child, or ſervant, ſhe is ſuch a mans <hi>wife,</hi> or it is ſuch a mans <hi>child,</hi> or they are ſuch a ones <hi>ſervants:</hi> thus are beleevers to be appropriated to God. You may ſay concerning a beleever, There goes the <hi>child</hi> of God. Gal. 3. 7. There goes the <hi>heire</hi> of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. Rom. 8. 17. Children not begotten according to the <hi>fleſh,</hi> but of the <hi>immortall, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible ſeed of the word.</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 23. You may ſay of them, 2. There goes the Lambs <hi>wife,</hi> the wife of the Prince of glory, the Kings daughter. Eph. 5. 29, 30, 31, 32. Hoſea 2. 18. You may ſay of them, 3. There goes one of Gods <hi>ſervants.</hi> 1 Cor. 7. 22. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham was ſtiled by Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech, <hi>the ſervant of the most high God. Paul</hi> often ſtiles himſelfe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184283:51"/> 
                        <hi>the ſervant of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Nay 4. They ſtand in the relation of <hi>members,</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt the head. 1 Cor. 6. 16. This is by reaſon of the neare myſticall unſpeakable <hi>Vnion</hi> that is betwixt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt and the ſoule. Joh. 15. 3. <hi>I in you, and you in me.</hi> We are <hi>fleſh of his fleſh and bone of his bone,</hi> Eph. 5. 29. 30. &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. So then? can you ſay of your <hi>wife, ſhe</hi> is mine? canſt thou ſay of thy <hi>child,</hi> it is mine? canſt thou ſay of any <hi>ſervant</hi> that thou keepeſt, he or ſhe is mine? Nay nearer yet: canſt thou ſay of thy right <hi>hand,</hi> or <hi>foot,</hi> or any <hi>member</hi> of thy body, it is mine? So is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever Chriſts: Chriſts <hi>purchaſe, poſſeſsion, Servant, wife, child, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, member, &amp;c. Beleevers then while they live are the Lords.</hi> Thats the firſt branch, and that is plain. Proceed we now to the ſecond, and that is,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:184283:51"/>
                     <head>2. Branch. <hi>That becauſe of it, it is his duty while he lives not to live to himſelfe but to the Lord.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In the opening and handling of this, I will doe theſe three things.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. I wil shew you, <hi>how a man may be ſaid to live to himſelfe, and what that meanes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. I will ſhew you, <hi>how it is the beleevers duty to live unto God, and what that meanes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. I will ſhew you, <hi>how the conſideration of this that a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever while he lives is the Lords, layeth an engagement upon his heart, while he lives, not to live to himſelfe but to the Lord.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Of all theſe briefly, and firſt of the firſt.</p>
                     <div n="1" type="section">
                        <head>How may a man be ſaid to live to himſelfe, and what doth that phraſe meane?</head>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:184283:52"/>
                        <p> A man may be ſaid to live to himſelfe, either in a <hi>Civill</hi> or in a <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>Theologicall</hi> ſenſe, in a <hi>Civill</hi> ſenſe a man may bee ſaid to live to himſelfe, <hi>When he is free from all relations,</hi> when he trades for himſelf, and lives upon his owne hand as we ſay; thus queſtionleſſe the beleever may live to himſelfe. Or 2. <hi>Civilly,</hi> a man may be ſaid <hi>to live to himſelfe,</hi> that is <hi>ſuo commodo,</hi> to his own <hi>back</hi> and <hi>belly</hi> meerly, that as we ſay <hi>none eates of his meat nor drinks of his cup, nor is a penny the better for him,</hi> thus a beleever will hardly live to himſelfe. Or 3. <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy</hi> a man is ſaid to <hi>live to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in reſpect of Communion,</hi> when he is <hi>nulli comes,</hi> a compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fit for none, either in regard of the <hi>moroſity,</hi> or <hi>ſullenneſſe</hi> of his temper. But none of theſe hits the ſenſe of the text, which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184283:52"/> (queſtionleſſe) is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of a <hi>privacy of civill life,</hi> but in a divine ſenſe; and ſo a man may live to himſelfe two wayes, none of both which are competent to a beleever. Not</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Formally;</hi> not to pleaſe himſelf; not following the corrupt dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of his owne fleſh, as the baſe prophane wretch, to whom the <hi>Devill</hi> doth but ſay <hi>goe, and he goeth;</hi> or come, and he cometh; and his baſe heart ſayes but <hi>doe this,</hi> and he <hi>doth it:</hi> this is often called in Scripture <hi>living to the fleſh,</hi> and <hi>living to ſin.</hi> Thus the beleever lives not to himſelfe. Nor</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Finally;</hi> a man may be ſaid to live to himſelfe, when all the actions of his life purſue but his owne worldly <hi>intereſts of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and wealth, and honour.</hi> The beleever in his life drives on Gods
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184283:53"/> 
                           <hi>intereſts,</hi> trades for glory, and acts for his Maſter; himſelfe is but a <hi>factor</hi> here in a ſtrange coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: whether he <hi>eates, or drinkes, or ſleeps, or trades,</hi> or <hi>whatever he doth, he doth it for the glory of God,</hi> whoſe factor he is. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 21. <hi>To me to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gaine,</hi> or (as others read it) <hi>[to me both in life and death, Chriſt is gain.]</hi> Thus I have explaned the firſt particular, and by opening of this, I have alſo given ſome light to the other, and in part ſhewed you what it is for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to <hi>dye to himſelfe,</hi> which I ſhall further enlarge my ſelfe upon by and by.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="section">
                        <head>The ſecond thing to be opened is what it is for a beleever to <hi>live to God,</hi> and <hi>how a beleever may be ſaid to live to the Lord.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>I will open it in three or four par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. 1. A beleever may be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:184283:53"/> ſaid to live to the Lord <hi>Ratione Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> by way of Right, owning, and acknowledging God to be his God, as a <hi>Sonne</hi> lives to his <hi>Father,</hi> and a <hi>Servant</hi> to his <hi>Master:</hi> wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chriſts <hi>livery,</hi> and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging himſelfe to be Chriſts <hi>Servant.</hi> Proclaming with <hi>David.</hi> Pſal. 116. 16. <hi>Truly Lord I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant, and the Sonne of thy handmaid: for thou hast looſed my bonds.</hi> Yea and this he will doe in all places, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies: if Jeſus Chriſt be named, he is not aſhamed to ſay (with M. Herbert) <hi>My Lord, and Maſter.</hi> He every where acknowledgeth his ſubjection, and duty to God, by his ſervice as his <hi>Maſter,</hi> by his homage as to his <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> by his dutifull feare as to his <hi>Father,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Prophet. Mal. 1. 6. <hi>If I be a father where is my honour, and if a maſter where is</hi>
                           <pb n="26" facs="tcp:184283:54"/> 
                           <hi>my feare?</hi> He every where honours God as his <hi>Father,</hi> and feares him as his <hi>Maſter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Secondly, The beleever lives to God <hi>formally.</hi> He followes the <hi>dictates</hi> of his <hi>word,</hi> and the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of his <hi>ſpirit.</hi> He is come into the world to doe his will, he knowes that for this end he was borne, and readily in the whole motion of his life ſayes, <hi>I delight to do thy will O my God.</hi> If God in his <hi>word</hi> or by his <hi>ſpirit</hi> ſayes to him <hi>Goe, he goes, Come, he comes, doe this, he doth it.</hi> He diſputes not the <hi>rebellion</hi> of his owne <hi>will,</hi> nor private <hi>intereſts</hi> of his owne <hi>ſpirit,</hi> againſt the <hi>will</hi> of God once <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed</hi> unto him.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, The beleever lives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God <hi>finally.</hi> The whole end of his life, of all his actions, words, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, recreations, is to <hi>glorify</hi> God, and he doth nothing but he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184283:54"/> prefaceth this queſtion to it, how may God have glory? what ſhall God get by this Action? this is the <hi>deſigne</hi> he drives, the <hi>intereſt</hi> he purſues, every of his <hi>arrowes</hi> are <hi>levelled</hi> at this <hi>white,</hi> and all his actions ordered to this <hi>end,</hi> it is his work to <hi>glorify God both in his body, and ſpirit,</hi> according to the Apoſtles exhortation. 1 Cor. 6. 20.</p>
                        <p>Laſtly, He lives unto God <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendently.</hi> Indeed this is rather a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving upon God, but yet it is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unto God too: <hi>The life which he now lives is by faith upon the Son of God.</hi> Gal. 2. 20. He cleaves unto God in all the Conditions, and all the Relations of his life; <hi>Thus he lives not to himſelfe but to the Lord.</hi> Yea and Thirdly,</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="section">
                        <head>The third branch, <hi>It is his duty therefore while he lives not to live to himſelfe,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184283:55"/> but to the Lord: becauſe while he lives he is the Lords.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Which is the third thing.</p>
                        <p>This is plaine if you doe but conſider what I ſaid before in the particular explanation of the firſt branch of the Doctrine, viz. How far the beleever while he lives <hi>is the Lords.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe he is the Lords pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe.</hi> What? ſhall I buy a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and ſhall he ſerve another Maſter? Shall I buy an houſe, and ſhall it rent to another Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord?</p>
                        <p n="2">2. <hi>Becauſe he is the Lords poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> See the Apoſtle preſſing this duty from both theſe Arguments 1 Cor. 6. 19, 20. <q>
                              <hi>What? know ye not, that your body is the temple of holy Ghoſt which is in you, and which you have of God, and you are not your owne, for yee are bought with a price, therefore glorify God, in your body</hi>
                              <pb n="29" facs="tcp:184283:55"/> 
                              <hi>and your ſpirit which are Gods.</hi>
                           </q> Yea and thirdly,</p>
                        <p n="3">3. <hi>Becauſe we are the Lords in ſo neare Relation.</hi> Would you take it well that your <hi>children,</hi> or <hi>apprentices</hi> which you maintaine ſhould <hi>live to themſelves?</hi> And trade for themſelves? or others? and not live to you and trade for you? That your wife ſhould live to another? Either <hi>formally or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,</hi> and not to you, whoſe ſhe is? And is there not as great an engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (Chriſtians!) lyes upon you to live to the Lord? you are his Children, his ſpouſes, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, nay nearer yet, his <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers:</hi> There is all reaſon in the world that you ſhould not live to your ſelves, but unto him. And thus I have done with the ſecond Branch of the Doctrine, viz.</p>
                        <q>That when the beleever lives he lives not to himſelfe but to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:184283:56"/> Lord, and it is his duty ſo to do, becauſe while he lives he is the Lords.</q>
                        <p>I paſſe to the third Branch.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>The third Branch, <hi>That when the beleever dies he dies not to himſelfe but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, and it is his duty ſo to doe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Here for the explanation of this Branch I ſhall do theſe two things.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew <hi>how a man may be ſaid to die to himſelfe, which the beleever doth not.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, I ſhall ſhew you <hi>what it is to die to the Lord, and how a beleever may be ſaid when he dies to die to the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div n="1" type="section">
                        <p n="1">1. I conceive a man may be ſaid to die to himſelf, 1. <hi>when him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is the cauſer, wiſher, or deſirer of his own death:</hi> thus <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> dyed to themſelves, and could not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:184283:56"/> ſtay Gods leiſure. The beleever is of another ſpirit.</p>
                        <p>Or Secondly, <hi>when in dying, or deſiring to die, he meerly aimes at his owne end;</hi> out of a conceit of the eaſe and reſt he ſhall be at, becauſe he knowes if he be in the grave, <hi>There the wicked ceaſe from troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, there the weary be at rest,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> paſſionately ſpake, <hi>c.</hi> 3. or to deliver himſelfe from <hi>obloquies,</hi> as <hi>Ionas, cap.</hi> 3. or to ſave himſelfe from <hi>danger,</hi> as <hi>Saul;</hi> or to be out of the horrors of a guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as <hi>Iudas:</hi> theſe men dyed, or would have dyed to themſelves.</p>
                        <p>Or thirdly, a man may be ſaid to die to himſelfe, <hi>when he doth no good by his death,</hi> declares not the <hi>glory</hi> of God, nor <hi>faith</hi> in God, but dyes like <hi>Nabal;</hi> though his ſpirit be not over-powred with <hi>diſeaſes,</hi> nor he robbed of his <hi>ſenſes,</hi> yet he dyes like a <hi>block.</hi> Now the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184283:57"/> beleever none of theſe wayes dyes to himſelfe. 1. He will not chooſe his owne ſpeare with <hi>Saul,</hi> nor twiſt his owne <hi>Halter</hi> with <hi>Iudas.</hi> He will not only aime at his owne eaſe, in his death, but if the Lord ſtops not his mouth by an over-powring diſeaſe, nor bereaves him of his ſence and ſpeech, he will be ſetting out the goodneſſe, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God with his very utmoſt breath; as this our precious Siſter, that had ſuch a mind of her jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney that ſhe could talke of nothing elſe.</p>
                        <p>I paſſe to the ſecond thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="section">
                        <head>Second Branch, To ſhew you, <hi>What it is for a Beleever to dye to the Lord, and how the beleever when he dyes will dye to the Lord.</hi> 
                        </head>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:184283:57"/>
                        <p> Firſt, <hi>he will dye at the Lords leaſure;</hi> he wil not haſten his death, nor dye the death of the wicked; his ſoule is indeed ſo greedy of <hi>glory,</hi> that he is continually ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after a diſſolution, and crying <hi>come Lord Ieſus, come quickly;</hi> but yet not ſo haſty, but he leaves God to his liberty, for ſo poor a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of time; this was <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe, 1 Phil. 23. 24. <hi>He had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be with Chriſt which was beſt of all:</hi> can you blame him for that? But yet (ſaith he) <hi>it is expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for you that I ſhould ſtay;</hi> I am content. Like a dutifull child that being abroad hath a deſire to ſee his friends, and is ſometimes wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, O that the holy-dayes were come, that he might goe home, and it may be he ſometimes writes to them for an horſe, but yet he is not ſo mad as to run home on foot, much leſſe to goe contrary
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184283:58"/> to his fathers mind.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, in dying <hi>he will not aime at his owne eaſe,</hi> but herein ſubmits himſelfe to the Lord, and that both for the <hi>time</hi> of his death, and alſo for the <hi>kind</hi> of it. 1. <hi>For the time of his death,</hi> See Phil. 23, 24. If <hi>Paul</hi> might judge himſelfe, he thinkes it would be beſt preſently to dye. But if it be more expedient for the Churches he ſhould live yet a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while, he is content; he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſends to his Father, to let him know his <hi>longing deſire to ſee him,</hi> but with all lets him know his <hi>reſignation</hi> to his wil, and adds, yet <hi>Father if it be your pleaſure I ſhould ſtay</hi> a quarter of a yeere or ſome few months longer I will <hi>ſubmit</hi> my <hi>will</hi> to your <hi>pleaſure.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And as for the time of his death, ſo alſo <hi>for the kind of his death:</hi> if his Father will have him come on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:184283:58"/> foot, or on horſe-back, ſo he goeth, he careth not, if he will have him goe on his ſwifteſt race nag or on the dulleſt jade in the ſtable; he as willingly will be carted as coached thither. Now ſaith <hi>Paul, I am ready to be offered.</hi> 
                           <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 6.</note> It is all one to him, to be ſent to heaven with a ſtroke, or linger out many days with this pretious one, that was ſeverall yeares on her journy to heaven, yet ſeemed not to be tyred with the length of the journy, or the ſlowneſſe of her horſe; ſhe knew whoſe work it was to ſwitch or ſpurr, and therefore held her owne hands. This is the true temper of a Chriſtian in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Lord, to be content though he hangs a long time, and that upon a croſſe, ſo the life and death of the Lord Ieſus may be made <hi>manifeſt in his fleſh,</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it all one whether he dye of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:184283:59"/> the plague, or a conſumption, a fever, or the ſtone; upon the rack, or at the ſtake; whether the ſword divides him, or the arrowes of the Lord pierce him, he dyes not to himſelfe but to the Lord.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, he dyes to the Lord, as aiming at the Lords <hi>glory</hi> in his death, &amp; thence is ſubmiting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to Gods will for all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, ſo alſo endeavouring to give glory to the Lord in his death, and bring the Lord glory by dying. Pauls <hi>bonds,</hi> &amp; <hi>Impriſonment</hi> brought glory to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 12, 13, 14. And this he may aime at dying ſeverall wayes. 1. By <hi>his quiet and patient ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unto God, in the meſſengers of death,</hi> Pſal. 39. 9. <hi>David</hi> was <hi>dumbe</hi> and <hi>knew not how to complain</hi> becauſe it was the Lords <hi>doing.</hi> Like Ely, <hi>It is the Lord let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi> Like Chriſt,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184283:59"/> 
                           <hi>Father</hi> (if it be poſſible) <hi>let this cup paſſe from me, yet not my will but thy will be done.</hi> He kiſſeth the ſtake, and imbraceth the flame. 2. If his death be violent, <hi>By undanted ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering at his death.</hi> Thus the blood of the Martyrs paid God a tribute of glory, by being the ſeed of the Church. O how glorious prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers were the Martyrs! That as it was ſaid of <hi>Samſon, the number of them that he flew at his death was more than thoſe he ſlew in his life:</hi> So we might ſay of them; The number of them that they ſpiritually <hi>quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> in their <hi>lives,</hi> was ſhort of them that were <hi>quickned</hi> by their <hi>deaths.</hi> Docter Taylor made it a plaine <hi>going home,</hi> and counted his journy to <hi>two ſtiles;</hi> whoſoever reads the ſtories of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> or the ſtories of the <hi>Martyrs</hi> under the ten perſecutions, or of late in thoſe reaking times of Q. <hi>Mary (that</hi>
                           <pb n="38" facs="tcp:184283:60"/> 
                           <hi>filled the land with innocent blood)</hi> will find this abundantly inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. 3. <hi>Whether it be a violent or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall death, they will bring glory to the Lord by ſpeaking ſomething to the glory of God at their death, ſome way or other ſetting out the glory of God, and his goodneſſe towards them, ſhewed to them in their life or death.</hi> Thus did many of the glorious Martyrs, and an abundant full proofe of this was this our glorious Siſter. O how buſy was ſhe to tell what the goodneſſe of God had been to her, to glorify his name, to direct, comfort, quicken! were not many of you warmed at the heart by her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall fire?</p>
                        <p>Thus the beleever dyes to the Lord, declaring his <hi>faith</hi> in God, <hi>Now I know my redeemer lives, and that I ſhall ſee him with theſe eyes.</hi> Yet ſo it may be, that a beleever,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:184283:60"/> through the nature or violence of his diſeaſe may bee a wanting to this duty; if the Lord ties his tongue who can help it? but if he ſuffers him but to <hi>open his lips, his mouth ſhall ſhew forth his praiſe.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſometimes, a beleever may dye in the <hi>dark</hi> in regard of the ſenſible <hi>enjoyments</hi> of Chriſts love, but even then though hee may complain of his own vileneſſe and unworthineſſe, yet it is a thouſand to one, but he <hi>gives glory</hi> to God; he dyes not like <hi>Nabal;</hi> not as <hi>fooles</hi> dye. I haſten to the laſt branch of the Doctrine, which is that</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="part">
                     <head>Fourth Branch, <hi>Beleevers in death are the Lords.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Shortly of it.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>The Lord owns them in Death,</hi> Pſa. 73. 26. <hi>Though my fleſh faileth, and my heart faileth, yet God is the ſtrength of my heart; and my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:184283:61"/> 
                        <hi>for ever.</hi> He ownes them in <hi>dying,</hi> he takes notice of their compoſing themſelves to ſleep, and hath newes brought him to heaven of every Saints ſickening and dying, he hearkeneth and heareth their death ſighes, and grownes, yea and after death more then ever; then the <hi>ſoul is returned to God,</hi> and imboſomed in him, and <hi>mortality is ſwallowed up of life,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. 6.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. They are the Lords then <hi>by Vnion;</hi> the <hi>head,</hi> and the <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> will be then as much one, yea more one then ever they were, they that were one in Grace, are made one in glory; as the ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Sun beames</hi> when they are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into the <hi>Sun,</hi> are more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly one with the <hi>Sun,</hi> then when there was a ſeeming <hi>diviſion</hi> of their <hi>vnity</hi> for the <hi>irradiation</hi> of the earth, ſo all the Saints which are
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184283:61"/> but as diſtinct beames of the Sun of Righteouſneſſe, when they ſhall be gathered into Chriſt, ſhall yet continue to be one with him, yea and more gloriouſly one then ever. The <hi>Bride</hi> is now made ready for the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and the private marriage day is come. The Bride of the <hi>Lambe</hi> is here but in her <hi>mourning gowne,</hi> yet Chriſt (who is a pure eſſence of infinite love) delights in her in that dreſſe, and even in that habit will not live from her; when ſhe dyes to the world, ſhe hath <hi>dreſt her head,</hi> and then is more <hi>lovely</hi> in his Eye, but by that time the day of <hi>judgment</hi> comes, ſhe wil be wholy, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly <hi>dreſt</hi> to come out to <hi>Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> and everlaſting <hi>banquetting</hi> in the <hi>chambers of love,</hi> with the King of Glory.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, When he dyes he is the Lords by <hi>neare Relation;</hi> this is an
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:184283:62"/> undoubted conſequence of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but yet a little more; Death breaks all <hi>Relations,</hi> but the <hi>Relation</hi> that is betwixt <hi>God</hi> &amp; the <hi>beleeving ſoule,</hi> and its <hi>knife</hi> is not ſharp enough <hi>to cut this</hi> aſunder; ſee this but in two inſtances, 1 Joſh. 2. God ſayes, <hi>Moſes my ſervant is dead.</hi> Dead; yet my ſervant: we cannot ſay, ſuch a one my ſervant is dead, or if we doe ſay ſo, it is but an improper phraſe of ſpeach; for if he be dead he is not <hi>my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant;</hi> he does me no worke, he takes none of my wages: We can ſay, ſuch a one, that <hi>was my ſervant</hi> is dead, but if the perſon be dead, the cord of our Relation is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Job ſpeaking of death, Job. 3. ſayes, <hi>There the ſervant is free from his Master:</hi> But God ſayes, <hi>Moſes my ſervant is dead,</hi> though he be <hi>dead,</hi> yet he is <hi>my ſervant.</hi> And we may ſay concerning any
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:184283:62"/> holy man, or woman, concerning this remarkable Saint, ſuch a one Gods <hi>deare Servant</hi> is dead: Dead, yet <hi>Gods ſervant;</hi> ſhe hath chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her room, and work, yea and her <hi>wages</hi> too, but not her <hi>Maſter,</hi> ſhe is but taken to be his <hi>chambermaid in glory,</hi> from being his <hi>Kitchin-maid in the world;</hi> her work was before <hi>below ſtaires,</hi> now it is <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</hi> Take but one inſtance more, it is, Joh. 11. 11. Chriſt ſayes, <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleeps, he ſleeps,</hi> yet he is <hi>Our friend.</hi> O ſweet! we ſay when ſuch a one dyes we have <hi>loſt</hi> a <hi>deare friend.</hi> But God loſeth not his relation by his <hi>Saints death,</hi> he is our <hi>friend</hi> then more than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſo are we his. And thus I have gone through the ſeverall branches of the Doctrine.</p>
                     <p>And now what a ſweet doctrine were here for application, if I had any time, but I muſt but
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:184283:63"/> hint at things, and lay the <hi>letters,</hi> and leave them to God to <hi>ſtampe</hi> upon your hearts.</p>
                     <p>I will apply it, or rather ſhew you how you may apply it, by way of Inſtruction, Reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Exhortation, and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>Firſt of all by way of <hi>Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> 
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> and ſo it might be very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, 1. To ſhew you the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite love of God, to poor <hi>duſt, and aſhes.</hi> That he will be pleaſed to owne us in <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>death;</hi> to come, and dwell in <hi>houſes made of clay,</hi> nay not in all the houſes of clay neither; ſome he will not beſtow the paines to make them <hi>cleane,</hi> and <hi>tenantable</hi> for himſelfe; ſome great famous built houſes, built of free ſtoned <hi>Nobility</hi> &amp; <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, learning</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> adorned with <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>eſteem</hi> in the world, he leaves to be an habitation for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:184283:63"/> 
                        <hi>Owles, and Oſtriches,</hi> and comes and dwels in the poor Cottages of his Elect ones. <hi>The poore of this world hath God choſen.</hi> God loves the houſe well in which he will dwell; <hi>you only have I knowne above all the Nations of the Earth, &amp;c.</hi> O mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy! that God ſhould ſay to one, that it may be hath not a rag to cover him with, nor a place where to lay downe his head, <hi>Here is the ſoule in which I have choſe to dwell, to pitch my name there;</hi> who are we that <hi>Our Lord ſhould come to us?</hi> we have not a room either in <hi>head</hi> or <hi>heart fit</hi> for to entertaine him. If he will come he muſt bring his ſtoole to ſit down on, and be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed with his own meat, and yet he will come and be a <hi>father,</hi> an <hi>huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> a <hi>friend,</hi> and call us his <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> his <hi>children,</hi> his <hi>ſpouſe,</hi> yea his <hi>members.</hi> Think, O think what honour it is to be allied to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:184283:64"/> the <hi>family</hi> of Heaven, yea <hi>incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated</hi> in it. It is a big word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, when they can ſay, my Coſen of <hi>Eſſex</hi> or <hi>Norfolk,</hi> &amp;c. to be allied to <hi>Earles, Dukes,</hi> &amp;c. We think we mightily ſpeak our honour, when he can ſpeake it; is it not a far greater when we can ſay, My brother of heaven, nay my <hi>Father,</hi> my <hi>Lord,</hi> my <hi>husband, &amp;c? Such honour have all his Saints.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, It might inſtruct us <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſt. </seg>2</label> 
                        <hi>of the happineſſe of beleevers both in life, and death;</hi> we are the Lords poſſeſſion, there is no feare of a bad <hi>Landlord.</hi> Are we his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe? his redeemed ones? no feare of any ſlavery then, his <hi>yoke</hi> is eaſy, his <hi>burthen</hi> is light, his <hi>ſervice</hi> a perfect <hi>freedome.</hi> Is he our <hi>Father,</hi> our <hi>Maſter,</hi> our <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> our <hi>friend?</hi> we have then one that is <hi>able</hi> to help us, <hi>willing</hi>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:184283:64"/> to ſuccour us, <hi>ready</hi> to pitty us; a kind father, a loving husband, a carefull maſter. <hi>The Lord is our Shepheard, what can we want?</hi> Surely nothing that <hi>All-ſufficiency</hi> can help us to. We are the Lords in our life; Nor is <hi>our portion in this life, Whether we live or dye we are the Lords:</hi> we are yet his <hi>friends,</hi> his <hi>ſervants,</hi> Joſ. 1. 2. Joh. 11. 11. We are yet his <hi>temple</hi> in which he doth more manifeſt his <hi>glory</hi> than in our <hi>tabernacle</hi> while it comes to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; we are yet his <hi>purchaſed poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion,</hi> Eph. 1. 16. Dying loſeth us not that <hi>friend.</hi> O happy, truly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and <hi>Bleſſed are they that dye in the Lord, for they rest from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> It was a leſſon that John was commanded to write, do you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it, It was written for your Inſtruction, and comfort. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye live or die, ye are the Lords.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, this may Inſtruct us <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtit. </seg>3</label>
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:184283:65"/> 
                        <hi>that there are but a very few that are true beleevers, that in death ſhall be the Lords.</hi> No more then thoſe that live to the Lord, and dye to the Lord. And ah! how few thoſe are? 1. What ſhall become of all <hi>prophane wretches, all drunkards, ſwearers, adulterers,</hi> all thoſe rabbles of wretches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. v. 8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 8, 10. that in ſtead of <hi>living to the Lord, live</hi> to the <hi>Devill,</hi> to their baſe <hi>luſts</hi> and <hi>corruptions,</hi> and all their ſtudy is, how to obey the fleſh, in the luſts of it? Ah Lord! what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of theſe poor wretches when they dye, when you ſhall cry out, <hi>Animula! quo vadis?</hi> poore ſoule whither goeſt thou? It was a dreadfull paſſage I lately heard to have been the dying breath of ſuch an one, <hi>Now goes my prore ſoule to pay all its debts.</hi> 2. What ſhall become of all <hi>thoſe that live to the</hi>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:184283:65"/> 
                        <hi>world,</hi> and make their gain the End of their life? whoſe whole life ſounds nothing elſe, But what <hi>ſhall we eat?</hi> or <hi>what ſhall we drink?</hi> or <hi>what ſhall we put on?</hi> What will you gaine (friends) when to <hi>gaine</hi> the world, you ſhall <hi>weep over</hi> your <hi>loſt poore ſoules;</hi> how will you ranſome your ſelves from the pit? And ſo for any other that make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing below God, the End of their lives. And ah! where ſhall we find a man concerning whom, we may pronounce this text, while he lived, he <hi>lived to the Lord,</hi> and when he dyed, <hi>he dyed to the Lord?</hi> And yet this muſt be pronounced of all thoſe that when they <hi>dy ſhall be the Lords:</hi> O remember your latter end!</p>
                     <p n="4">4. This may inſtruct us <hi>in the right way, to dye comfortably.</hi> He that knowes he is the <hi>Lords</hi> cannot dye ſadly; now wouldſt thou find
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:184283:66"/> this? while thou liveſt, <hi>live to the Lord: when thou dyeſt, dye to the Lord.</hi> O the ſweetneſſe of <hi>perfumed</hi> death to the Saint! I remember I have heard of an holy man, that when he was about to dye, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to this effect. <hi>Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were all the honors, pleaſures, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments of the world on one hand, and death on the other, I would ſcorne them, and imbrace this.</hi> O get your hearts into ſuch a frame, which cannot be without making the Lord (while you live) the end of your life and actions.</p>
                     <p>Fiftly, this may further inſtruct <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſt. </seg>5</label> us, <hi>Of the great difference betwixt the wicked, and the Godly, in their deaths, and of the Reaſon of it.</hi> The worldling <hi>lives to himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>dyes to himſelfe,</hi> perhaps he makes <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way himſelfe,</hi> or dyes <hi>murmuringly,</hi> and <hi>blaſphemes</hi> God, he cannot give God a good word at the laſt. The
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:184283:66"/> beleever could be content to be preſent with the Lord, yet he waites Gods leaſure and patiently ſubmits to what death God will have him dye, whether it be Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or Violent, ſad or joyfull, ſhort or tedious, and whatever his death be, he dyes, <hi>joyfully.</hi> The One is <hi>loth</hi> to <hi>dye</hi> and cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide to think of ſhaking hands with ſo many Gods as he hath here below; the other dyes <hi>cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> and in his death gives glory to God. The Reaſon of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is plain Enough. The Saint, 1. Hath lived to God. 2. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to dye unto the Lord. 3. In death as well as in his life aimes at the glory of God. 4. Knowes that in death he ſhall be the Lords. The other, hath lived to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. 2. Aimes at nothing in dying but himſelfe. 3. Knowes that if he dyes his ſoule ſinks in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:184283:67"/> hell for ever, can you blame the man for being loth to goe into <hi>Everlaſting Burnings?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſecond uſe may be <hi>Terror</hi> 
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>2</label> to thoſe that neither regard while they live to live to the Lord, nor when they dye to dye to the Lord, all thoſe mentioned in the former uſe, that live to their luſts, and pleaſures, to the world, &amp;c. Should here be deeply reproved, Take on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two places to reprove you, Iſa. 50. 11. Eccl. 11. v. 9.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. This doctrine may be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by way of Exhortation, And, O that I could perſwade for God this day, ſome or other to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a life to him, every one ſayes, <hi>O that I might dye the death of the Righteous, that my latter end might be like his!</hi> but alas! who is there that lives according to his wiſh? wouldſt thou bee the Lords when thou dyeſt? <hi>live not then to thy</hi>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:184283:67"/> 
                        <hi>ſelfe but to the Lord,</hi> Live not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy <hi>owne luſts,</hi> live not to thy <hi>owne ends,</hi> but live <hi>by Gods law</hi> and <hi>to Gods glory:</hi> who would be the Lords when he dyes, he muſt be ſo while he lives; if God dwell with thy ſoule in life, thy ſoul ſhall dwell with him in death. O, leave trading for your ſelves, you ſpend your ſtrength for nothing, and your money for that which will not profit. <hi>What ſhall it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thee to gaine all the world, and loſe thy owne poore ſoule? Or what wilt thou give in Exchange for it?</hi> But I paſſe on (my time being expired, and the whole doctrine being practicall.)</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Let every beleever, look upon this as an Engagement of his ſoule to God, that <hi>In life and death he is the Lords;</hi> And from hence learne, while he <hi>lives to live to the Lord;</hi> and when <hi>he dyes to dye to the Lord.</hi>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:184283:68"/> To whom ſhould the <hi>ſervant</hi> live but to the <hi>maſter?</hi> the <hi>wife,</hi> but to the <hi>huſband?</hi> the <hi>child,</hi> but to the <hi>father?</hi> and the <hi>Saint,</hi> but to his <hi>Saviour?</hi> O quicken up your ſoules to this life, from this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; your <hi>engagments</hi> to God are high, let your <hi>life</hi> be <hi>anſwerable;</hi> lay out the <hi>talents</hi> he hath given you, for his <hi>advantage;</hi> drive on his <hi>Intereſt,</hi> purſue his <hi>ends. You are bought with a price. Bloody</hi> friends have you been to Chriſt, who in this hath excel'd the love of men, that <hi>while you were yet enemies he dyed for you, that by his death</hi> you might <hi>be reconciled to God.</hi> Let God never complain concerning you, as he once complained of his Iſraelites, Iſa. 1. 2. <hi>I have nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed children, but not to my ſelfe; I have brought them up but they have rebelled againſt me. O let your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation be ſuch as becometh the</hi>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:184283:68"/> 
                        <hi>Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> You live in God, live alſo unto God: <hi>For none of us liveth to himſelfe, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Laſtly, it may be applyed by way of Conſolation, and ſo I ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it more generally, or more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly relating to this occaſion.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Generally.</hi> It may admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>comfort</hi> unto us, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our owne deaths. 2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our friends deaths.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Concerning our owne death.</hi> What, art thou afraid to dye Chriſtian? To <hi>let thy ſoule returne to God that gave it?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Conſider firſt, <hi>Haſt thou not lived to God?</hi> Haſt thou been his <hi>factor,</hi> and art thou afraid to ſee him? his child, and art thou afraid of returning to thy <hi>Fathers houſe?</hi> can the faithfull Servant feare a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to his Maſter?</p>
                     <p>Conſider ſecondly, <hi>Hath it not been thy deſire to glorify God, as he</hi>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:184283:69"/> 
                        <hi>pleaſeth to be glorified?</hi> Thou haſt <hi>finiſhed</hi> thy <hi>courſe, runne</hi> thy <hi>race, done</hi> thy <hi>work,</hi> God hath had his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired glory of thee in thy life, and now his will is that thou ſhouldſt glorify him by dying to him.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Remember that in death, <hi>thou art the Lords. To dye to me is gaine</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>While we</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 23. 1 Cor. 5. 6.</note> 
                        <hi>are at home in the body, we are abſent from the Lord.</hi> At <hi>home</hi> doth the Apoſtle call it? a ſtrange home! where we have neither <hi>father,</hi> nor brethren, nor ſcarce ſo much as a <hi>friend.</hi> By death thou doeſt but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne like the <hi>ſunbeame</hi> into the body of the Sun: Thou art yet the Lords friend.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It may comfort us concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the death of ſuch our friends, as <hi>while they lived, lived to the Lord.</hi> Haſt thou a beleeving friend dead?</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Conſider that <hi>he, or ſhe, is</hi>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:184283:69"/> 
                        <hi>where they would be;</hi> it is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of every Saint to glorify God in that manner that he deſires to be glorified by them, to ſerve him any where, whether in the <hi>Kitchin</hi> or the <hi>Parlour</hi> it makes no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to them, giving glory to him is that they deſire. Gods will is revealed when thy friend dyes that he would have them come, and ſerve at <hi>court.</hi> Why weepeſt thou? Thy friend hath his wiſh; ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt which is beſt of all.</p>
                     <p>Nay,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Conſider <hi>thy friend hath not only his wiſh but his greateſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> thy friend is the Lords, and that in a more ſpeciall, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious manner, now than ever; Let this ſtop thy mouth: Thy friend is with the Lord, he hath him, he ownes him: the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beame is but <hi>in-bodyed</hi> in the <hi>Sun,</hi>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:184283:70"/> the <hi>blood</hi> is but runne to the <hi>heart.</hi> Ah! but we have loſt! What haſt thou loſt Chriſtian? 1. <hi>Was not thy friend the Lord's while he lived?</hi> the Lords by right, thine only by loan? was he not the Lords purchaſe? &amp; shall not the Lord come when he pleaſe, and take poſſeſſion of it? may he not pull it down, &amp; build it up again, at his pleaſure? ſhal he not <hi>do what he will his own?</hi> we uſe to ſay, <hi>A man may take his owne where ever he finds it;</hi> hath not God the like liberty? he hath found one of his lambes in thy paſture; it will argue an ill mind in thee not to bee willing he ſhould take it home; what? becauſe hee hath let thee keep it for him, wilt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his right? His Saint can be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of heaven no longer.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Is he not the Lords poſſeſsion?</hi> and ſhal not God take his houſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his owne hands if he will when
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:184283:70"/> the tenants leaſe is out? God uſeth not to renew leaſes: Once I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe he did it to Hezekiah, but his ordinary cuſtome is, as leaſes of Saints lives expire, to take them into his owne hands, till he hath got in all his redeemed <hi>morgages,</hi> and the full day of redeeming the <hi>purchaſed poſſeſsion</hi> ſhall come. Mayeſt thou remove thy <hi>houſe,</hi> and ſhall not God <hi>remove his</hi> whither he pleaſes? The Saints are Gods <hi>dwelling place,</hi> here he lives in <hi>Cotta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of clay, now when the beleever dyes God puls downe his <hi>clay-Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages,</hi> intending to fetch away the timber and bricks, to build up himſelfe a temple in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of glory.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Nay are they not <hi>the Lords by nearer relation than thine?</hi> ſhall not the <hi>father</hi> take home his <hi>child,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Schoolmaſter</hi> ſhall loſe the beſt <hi>Scholler</hi> of his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:184283:71"/> 
                        <hi>ſchoole?</hi> ſhall not the husband take home his wife, becauſe her <hi>friend</hi> ſhall loſe a good <hi>compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> Hath God any thing from thee but his owne? wouldſt not thou take it ill, if thy friend ſhould keep thy wife or child, for his owne pleaſure, when thou ſendſt for them after a long abſence?</p>
                     <p>Laſtly conſider! <hi>ſhouldſt not thou thy ſelfe, live to, and rejoyce in, the glory of God?</hi> Earth is a <hi>loſer</hi> of what was none of its owne ever, but heaven is a gainer, there is one <hi>Saint</hi> more there, one <hi>ſtarre</hi> more in the <hi>firmament</hi> of glory. Wilt thou <hi>weep</hi> becauſe thy <hi>friend</hi> hath a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and one <hi>jewell</hi> more is ſet in Chriſt <hi>diademe?</hi> ſhould not the child rejoyce at the increaſe of his fathers family? If at the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the <hi>family</hi> of Grace, then ſurely at the <hi>Increaſe</hi> of the <hi>houſhold</hi> of glory. There's one ſervant more
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:184283:71"/> added to the <hi>Bedchamber:</hi> Thy <hi>friend</hi> lived to the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>died to the Lord,</hi> and now in Death is <hi>the Lords,</hi> and more the Lords than ever.</p>
                     <p>I have done with my Doctrine, and my generall Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Let me add a little in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular relating to this occaſion.</p>
                     <p>You that mourne for this our <hi>ſiſter removed,</hi> Mourn not, neither weep: while ſhe lived, <hi>ſhe lived not to her ſelfe, but to the Lord, when ſhe died, ſhe dyed not to her ſelfe, but to the Lord. In her life ſhe was the Lords,</hi> and now in her death, I queſtion not but ſhe is <hi>the Lords.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You know it is not my cuſtome to ſpeak any thing concerning any upon theſe occaſions, But there are two ſorts of perſons, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whom I think it is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that if they have <hi>lived to the Lord while they lived,</hi> and dyed to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:184283:72"/> the Lord in their death, their examples ſhould be held out like <hi>Dorcas</hi> her clothes. 1. <hi>Eminent perſons in the Magiſtracie.</hi> 2. <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent preachers in the Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Of the firſt ſort ſhe was not, Not of the <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>great perſons</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> but out of a poor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily did the Lord chuſe this <hi>elect</hi> veſſell, to declare the <hi>Riches of the glory of his grace in.</hi> But you ſhall pardon me the expreſſion, if I ſay, that while ſhe lived, ſhe was an <hi>Eminent preacher,</hi> and give her the character which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our gave S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſhe was a <hi>burning, and a ſhining light;</hi> and I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, did <hi>more good,</hi> to poore ſoules, in the three yeares of her ſickneſſe, by <hi>telling them her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, directing, quickning, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting, ſtrengthening, ſatisfying, them,</hi> than God hath honoured any of us who have been prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:184283:72"/> of his word, to doe in much more time. I meane not that ſhe was a <hi>Pulpit-preacher,</hi> No, God had taught her to be wiſe to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, ſhe preached as <hi>Noah,</hi> by <hi>making the Ark,</hi> nay more, as <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla &amp; Aquila,</hi> by privately inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting others in the wayes of God.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall ſpeake but little of her, who while ſhe lived ſpake her ſelfe ſo much, I meane the <hi>ſtrength, and grace of God in her ſelf,</hi> for I muſt not exalt her, whoſe conſtant deſigne, and practice, was ſo much to <hi>debaſe</hi> her ſelfe, and all <hi>creatures,</hi> that the <hi>Creator</hi> might have the glory of all.</p>
                     <p>I ſhal not commend her for her <hi>mor all vertues,</hi> and naturall duties, which is too uſual upon ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as theſe (ſurely becauſe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things cannot be ſpoken.) But I shall ſet out her example to you, ſo as to exalt the <hi>infinite grace</hi> of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:184283:73"/> God towards her, and to let you ſee, <hi>who they are</hi> whom the Lord delighteth to honour, and how ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable it is to him, for <hi>yong ones</hi> to returne to their Father early, and for the poor to receive his goſpell. Give me but leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat my text, and Sermon over her, and I have done.</p>
                     <q>While ſhe lived, ſhe lived to the Lord, when ſhe dyed, ſhe dyed not to her ſelfe, but to the Lord.</q>
                     <p>It was but a little acquaintance I had of her, not yet two full years, in which time too, my multitude of occaſions were too much ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to my happines, in denying me ſo many <hi>opportunities</hi> of ſeeing her, as I deſired. I ſhall not ſpeak any thing, from others, but only <hi>what I have heard, and ſeen will I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare.</hi> Her whole time, ſince I knew her, was a <hi>Schooling</hi> time of Affliction (without any ceſſation)
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:184283:73"/> As I remember ſhe wanted ſome yeares of thirty, when ſhe dyed; and for three yeares and upward before that time, ſhe was Gods <hi>cloſe priſoner;</hi> and the greateſt part of that time (ſo bitter was her cup) was ſpent in her <hi>bed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I have heard her relating the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of her <hi>converſion,</hi> and for that I ſhall referr you to her owne account penned (by a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">See the precedent Relation.</note> friend) from her owne mouth. Her <hi>life</hi> was a <hi>life</hi> of afflictions. 1. <hi>Inward,</hi> then <hi>outward.</hi> Inward, by the temptations of the Devil, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of conſcience, and ſuch uſuall pangs as accompany the firſt birth: beſides that her God was ſometimes afterward behind the <hi>Curtain,</hi> and when he hid his face ſhe was troubled; when after much ſeeking, ſhe had found <hi>him whom her ſoule loved,</hi> and had got inward peace, that ſhe was, as it were
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:184283:74"/> rapt into the third heavens, then <hi>leſt ſhe ſhould be exalted above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhe had a thorn in the fleſh given to buffet her,</hi> God viſited her with a long, and tedious affliction, how ſhe demeaned her ſelfe in the beginning of it, what ſhe met with, how ſhe conquered, you may take from her owne mouth in the precedent Relation: I ſhall only ſupply the <hi>Chronicle</hi> of her dayes where her owne Relation ceaſed.</p>
                     <p>We commonly ſay Affliction is a ſpending time, it was not a beginning to her but it was a <hi>grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time of grace.</hi> The firſt time I came to viſit her (when I was but a ſtranger to her and to this City) I remember her firſt queſtion was, <hi>Sir I beſeech you tell me how I may glorify God in my affliction.</hi> I told her, either by <hi>patient ſubmitting</hi> to his <hi>hand,</hi> and <hi>quieting our</hi>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:184283:74"/> 
                        <hi>ſelves in his will,</hi> acknowledging his righteouſneſſe, &amp;c. Or by <hi>Speaking to his glory to others, &amp;c.</hi> For the paſſive part, it was a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhe had ſo well learned, that no diſcontent could either be read in her carriage or countenance, nor a repining word be heard from her lipps. And it was no light Affliction, for a <hi>young</hi> and <hi>Active</hi> body in its ſtrength to have Gods <hi>fetters</hi> laid upon it, and to be kept ſo <hi>cloſe a priſoner,</hi> as ſhe was, ſo long a time. But her God had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued her ſpirit to the feet of his owne will. The latter and <hi>Active</hi> part ſhe ſo practiſed, that her chamber was as a room of <hi>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe,</hi> none came in there, but went away <hi>Inſtructed,</hi> or <hi>Satisfied,</hi> or <hi>quickned,</hi> or ſome way or other <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</hi> The greateſt part of her work was <hi>Angelicall,</hi> a ſpeaking well of God, <hi>admiring</hi> and <hi>exalting</hi> his
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:184283:75"/> 
                        <hi>free grace,</hi> telling what he had done for her ſoule; yet ſhe remembred, that while ſhe was in the body ſhe had a duty to doe to others, and never did any labour more for God with the ſoules of others than this pretious one. Grace had made her <hi>eloquent;</hi> her <hi>birth,</hi> and <hi>breeding</hi> was meane, but the Lord had given her the tongue of the <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</hi> O the abundance of grace that <hi>was powred out into her lipps!</hi> I appeale to you, did not your hearts burne within you when you heard her ſpeak, the Excellency of ſenſe, ſpirituall ſenſe? I ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (as my occaſions permitted) went to viſit her, and while I thought to ſpeak, my eares ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced my tongue, and gave her leave to be the preacher, for the gain of thoſe in the room, and that I my ſelf might learn <hi>Righteouſnes:</hi> who ever heard her, mentioning her
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:184283:75"/> affliction? diſcourſing of any worldly thing? O that my tongue were ſo ſanctified! ſhe ſeemed to have loſt all ſenſe of <hi>Affliction,</hi> and while ſhe was in the body, to have been out of it; ſhe would often call upon thoſe yong ones that were babes of grace and came frequently to viſit her to labour after more <hi>communion</hi> with God. I remember one thing ſhe would often Vrge, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to remember it, viz. <hi>The excellency of the benefit the ſoule might reape by private prayer.</hi> She told you for this what was her and (if you be not your owne foes) may alſo be your experience. To make my diſcourſe ſhort, The time of her life grew ſhort, and as ſhe grew <hi>nearer</hi> the <hi>Earth,</hi> ſo ſhe grew more <hi>heavenly</hi> in her <hi>Hallelujahs,</hi> making of it then her onely work to <hi>Glorify God,</hi> by <hi>admiring</hi>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:184283:76"/> his grace, and exalting his name. I went to viſit her the day before the Lord took her to himſelf, I found her bereaved of moſt of her <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> but yet God gave her the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ſpeech,</hi> which ſhe ceaſed not to improve to his glory. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of her friends were <hi>weeping</hi> over her, ſhe was diſcourſing of the <hi>Creators Excellency,</hi> and the <hi>Creatures vanity,</hi> and that in ſuch language, that one would have thought ſhe had had the tongue of the <hi>Eloquent</hi> as well as the <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent:</hi> And ſo inceſſant was ſhe in that her <hi>ſpirituall worke,</hi> that ſhe would ſpeake even till ſhe had loſt her <hi>ſpeech,</hi> and pawſing a little (to recover her ſelfe) renewed her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to the admiration of my ſelfe, and thoſe others that heard her; ſhe had ſo far loſt her <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> that upon ſuch pawſes ſhe ordinarily forgat what she had
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:184283:76"/> ſaid, and renewing her diſcourſe, would either <hi>beg the help</hi> of the ſtanders by, or <hi>goe on</hi> upon ſome new, but (as heavenly) diſcourſe; to give thee a taſt thereof, take what I took that day from her own mouth Her words were theſe:</p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>I tell you (friends) if any Chriſtian ſit down ſhort of Chriſt, he ſhall faile; what is your duties, your righteouſnes, but a menſtruous cloath, loathſome to your ſelves, abominable to God? Our boaſting is excluded, we can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, what ſhould we ſtay in any thing that we cannot doe? O ſet up no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of your own; Let God have all, your ſelves are nothing. I will tell you my friends, my own experience, I have found, the creature is nothing, God is an Ocean, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>[Here her ſpeech fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and pawſing till she had recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her ſelf, she was not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what she ſpake laſt, but went on]</p>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:184283:77"/>
                     <q>
                        <hi>O the depth! the height! the length! the breadth! of Gods eternall decrees of love! Of his love in Christ to poore creatures. Study that Ocean; It may be ſome of you have known what that Fountaine, that Ocean of love is. Now whatſoever the ſoule ſets up, or eſteems beſides that, is but a ſhadow, a fancy. Let a man ſit never ſo long by a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, when he removeth, he cannot car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it away with him: If we get the ſubſtance, that will alſo carry the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow with it; If you get the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, you get both ſubſtance and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; whatever you have without him, is but the ſhadow without the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; follow not after ſhadowes, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue them not: ſtrive after Chriſt, and you ſhall in time ſee much of God. Sit not ſtill becauſe you ſee ſome difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the purſuance of this; there is ſcarce any of you but if you knew where to get</hi> 5 <hi>or</hi> 20 <hi>ſhillings, but would riſe up early, and worke hard to get it.</hi>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:184283:77"/> 
                        <hi>O why are not Chriſtians covetous? why ſhould not they be ambitious? Aas! the work is ſmall, why wil you ſit ſtill. But take heed of resting in your performances; doe them, but reſt not in them. Do not think of going to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Ordinances, and duties enough. Alas! what are publike Ordinances and duties, if they be not followed on by private prayer, and ſeeking God in ſecret? O ſeek him in ſecret, ſo you ſhall find him, and that ſhall make you love him more. But when you have done thus, reſt not in it, for I tell you again, if you ſit downe any where ſhort of Chriſt, you loſe all, whatſoever you think you enjoy, look higher then your ſelves, than your bare performances,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And if you looke well into them, you will ſee nothing in them, but abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of cauſe to be aſhamed. Nothing ſhort of Christ (I tell you againe) can make you acceptable, or amiable to God. It hath in it the baſeneſſe of our</hi>
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:184283:78"/> 
                        <hi>corrupted fleſh. What if you thinke a good thought? (which yet you cannot doe of your ſelves) if you reſt in it, it is naught. Chriſtianity is a work, the naturall man knowes. Alas! poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures think it is, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>Here her ſpeech failed, and she again pawſed. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saturday, my private ſtudies called me off, and I ſaw her no more, she dying the next day: But by the report of her friends, she continued her work, till God ſaid, <hi>It is enough,</hi> and then she quietly ſurrendred her ſoule to him that redeemed it. What paſſages she had nearer her death I shall omit, being not an ear-witneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Thus I have now ſet before you her holy <hi>Example,</hi> and have shewed you, how while she lived, <hi>ſhe lived not to her ſelf, but unto the Lord, and when ſhe dyed, ſhe dyed not to her ſelf, but to the Lord.</hi> And now to what purpoſe (doe you thinke) have I
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:184283:78"/> done all this? What, meerly to commend her? God forbid; But 1. <hi>For the glory of God.</hi> 2. <hi>For your good.</hi> 1. <hi>For the ſetting out Gods glory,</hi> in the <hi>riches of his free grace,</hi> 1. That he would reveale himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o <hi>ſuch a Babe,</hi> when he conceales himſelfe from the wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. 2. <hi>That paſsing by the great men, and rich men of the earth, he would chuſe this meane one</hi> (in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of others) <hi>to make knowne ſuch a fulneſſe of grace in of all kind of grace,</hi> both for her <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> as I have never before in any met with the like. It is rare to ſee one that hath ſo much both <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> as this precious one had, to her laſt houre.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, I have done it for your good. You have ſeene a <hi>quickning Example,</hi> and heard <hi>quickning words,</hi> the Lord give to me and you <hi>quickned</hi>
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:184283:79"/> 
                        <hi>hearts.</hi> Learne hence,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>You that are young, O ſlip not your golden Age.</hi> God delights much in young ones, reveales him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe much to babes that begin their life to him.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>You that are mean in the world,</hi> learne to <hi>walke with God,</hi> to keep cloſe to Chriſt; you may be richer in the grace of Chriſt, than the great men your Rulers.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Let all learne to be carefull of reſting in any thing ſhort of Chriſt:</hi> It was her <hi>counſell,</hi> O let her dying words ſticke faſt; she was full of duties, holy in her conſtant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, yet nothing but Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts her.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Let all learne from her, <hi>though not to reſt in duties, yet to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them, and that in ſecret.</hi> O be much with God in your cloſets, she tels you how ſweet it will be.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Learne from her Example
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:184283:79"/> 
                        <hi>to be holy, yet humble, her knowledge puffed her not up;</hi> yet I dare ſay, she had a great deale more of heaven in her, than ſome hundreds of thoſe that thinke they know enough to be Preachers: she was as heavenly as they, but not ſo proud and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Learn from her <hi>to lay in grace betimes.</hi> The Winter may come ſuddenly, her ſnow was fallen early.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Learne from her, <hi>in affliction to poſſeſſe your ſonles with patience, to remember it is Gods hand, and be ſtill.</hi> Who heard her murmure?</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Learne from her, <hi>to tell others what God hath done for your ſoules.</hi> This she made her work.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Learne from her, <hi>to reprove, direct, comfort, quicken, ſtrengthen thoſe that are your brethren.</hi> This was her work upon all occaſions.</p>
                     <p>In ſhort, learne from her exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Not to live to your ſelves,</hi>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:184283:80"/> 
                        <hi>but to the Lord, and when you dye, not to dye to your ſelves, but to the Lord, that both in life and death you may be the Lords.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>There came to my hands a ſheet written cloſe, containing ſeverall promiſes, which ſhe by her dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent reading had gathered up to ſute her ſoule in the time of need, indeed, ſo many, and ſo aptly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that it would cauſe admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to conſider how ſhe could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them in her memory, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily find them as they lye ſcattered in the Booke of God (without the help of a Concordance). But in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard theſe ſheets have ſwell'd too far already, and in regard the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Skippon</hi> on the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>Leigh</hi> on the Promiſes. The Saints Legacy.</note> are already ſweetly rank'd (in ſeverall Books printed) I thought good to omit the inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them. Now to the God of grace be Honour and Glory.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:184283:80"/>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
